<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY __nef-starter-app-setup__dr4w0y2f SYSTEM "../nef-reusable-content/nef-starter-app-setup.xml">
<!ENTITY __nef-key-features__dr4qnp41 SYSTEM "../nef-reusable-content/nef-key-features.xml">
<!ENTITY __nef-project-file__dr4s5f91 SYSTEM "../nef-reusable-content/nef-project-file.xml">
<!ENTITY __web-file__dr4thoqz SYSTEM "../nef-reusable-content/web-file.xml">
]>
<article>
  <title>Books Application Tutorial</title>

  <section>
    <title>Objectives</title>

    <para>The Books Application is a project meant to get you familiar with
    the <acronym>NEF</acronym> development by creating a simple but complete
    and functional real world application. The Books Application deals with
    the user interface as well as the back end part of the application. This
    involves the database access and the implementation of business logic. The
    Books Application will lead you through everything it takes to get an
    actual application up and running with special focus on developing the SQL
    and data management layers of your application.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Learning Objectives Checklist</title>

      <para>At the end of this tutorial, you should be able to
      understand:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the NEF Application Directory Structure</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the NEF Project File</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>how to set up the sample application</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>use of NEF Starter Application</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>creation and testing of Data Layer</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>creation and testing of Presentation Layer</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Assumptions</title>

    <para>For the purpose of this tutorial, we will be assuming that you
    installed the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Java Developer Kit (JDK) 1.2, 1.3 or 1.4</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A Servlet Container (application server) supporting the Servlet
        2.2 or higher specification</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>We assume that you are using the default port
    <literal>8080</literal> for your web server. If you chose different values
    for the installation path andthe port number, you should substitute the
    paths and the URLs in our example with your values as needed. This
    tutorial also assumes your familiarity with XML, SQL, Java, Servlets and
    JDBC.</para>
  </section>

  &__nef-starter-app-setup__dr4w0y2f;

  <section>
    <title>Key Concepts</title>

    <para>This section outlines some of the important, global concepts that
    you should be familiar with before embarking on developing your own
    applications.</para>

    &__nef-key-features__dr4qnp41;

    &__nef-project-file__dr4s5f91;

    &__web-file__dr4thoqz;
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Functionality</title>

    <para>The NEF Books Application is a small application meant to be used
    for a personal library of books. It allows you to track the books you have
    and add more books to your collection or edit information stored about
    existing books. It also allows you to search your collection for a
    particular book based on your own custom search criteria.</para>

    <para>The overall functionality of the application is limited but
    complete. As such it demonstrates a few of the main types of data
    manipulation that developers need to take care of in every application. In
    the end, the goal is to show you just how much power can be wielded with
    just a few lines of XML and Java code when armed with the strength of
    Sparx.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Design</title>

    <section>
      <title>Application Design</title>

      <para>The Books Application is designed around the basic Sparx
      components. It will use static SQL and associated reports to help you
      track the books stored in the application. Searches, on the other hand,
      require a dynamically generated SQL in the form of a Query
      Definition.</para>

      <para>The last aspect to take care of is the data storage. It is
      possible to use expensive abd overkill (in all certainty) database like
      Oracle for this application. Instead, the data storage of choice is the
      Java-based embedded database that is included in the Sparx Starter
      Application: <productname>HypersonicSQL</productname><footnote>
          <para>To learn more about <productname>HypersonicSQL, please go to
          <ulink
          url="http://hsqldb.sourceforge.net/">http://hsqldb.sourceforge.net/</ulink></productname></para>
        </footnote>. All the application components are included in the
      <filename>project.xml</filename> file for the Books Application. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Database Design</title>

      <para>The Books Application deals with books and only books. Therefore,
      the information that needs to be stored in the database will be about
      books. The four pieces of information that the Books Application will
      store for this example are its ID, name, author, genre and ISBN. Of
      these, the genre is the only one that can be common across multiple
      books. In database language, the genre (book type) has a one-to-many
      relationship with the books.<figure>
          <title>Basic E-R Diagram for Books Application Database</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-books-app-schema.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para>The figure shows the entity-relationship diagram for the data we
      will be using. The database for the Books Application will be designed
      to store each entity (and its attributes) in a separate table. As with
      the application design, the database design will become clearer when it
      is implemented later in this tutorial.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Creating the Data Layer</title>

    <para>With the empty (Starter) application successfully created and
    running, it is time to work on the backbone of the Books Application: the
    database. </para>

    <section>
      <title>Setting up the Database</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Schema</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Unit Testing the Schema</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Generating the Data Description Language</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Generating the SQL</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Unit Testing the SQL</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Creating the Presentation Layer</title>

    <para></para>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Home Page</title>

      <para></para>

      <section>
        <title>Unit Testing the Home Page</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Add Books Page</title>

      <para></para>

      <section>
        <title>Unit Testing the Add Books Page</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Edit Book Page</title>

      <para></para>

      <section>
        <title>Unit Testing the Edit Book Page</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Delete Book Page</title>

      <para></para>

      <section>
        <title>Unit Testing the Delete Book Page</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Search Books Page</title>

      <para></para>

      <section>
        <title>Unit Testing the Search Books Page</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Console Page</title>

      <para></para>

      <section>
        <title>Unit Testing the Console Page</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Sample Apps Home Page</title>

      <para></para>

      <section>
        <title>Unit Testing the Sample Apps Home Page</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Console Application</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Moving to Another Database</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</article>