<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY __nef-assumptions__drd5ufsf SYSTEM "../nef-reusable-content/nef-assumptions.xml">
<!ENTITY __nef-starter-app-setup__dr4w0y2f SYSTEM "../nef-reusable-content/nef-starter-app-setup.xml">
<!ENTITY __nef-key-features__dr4qnp41 SYSTEM "../nef-reusable-content/nef-key-features.xml">
<!ENTITY __nef-project-file__dr4s5f91 SYSTEM "../nef-reusable-content/nef-project-file.xml">
<!ENTITY __web-file__dr4thoqz SYSTEM "../nef-reusable-content/web-file.xml">
<!ENTITY __nef-project-file-tags-descr__drcg7alc SYSTEM "../nef-reusable-content/nef-project-file-tags-descr.xml">
]>
<article>
  <title>Books Application Tutorial</title>

  <section>
    <title>Objectives</title>

    <para>The Books Application is a project meant to get you familiar with
    the <acronym>NEF</acronym> development by creating a simple but complete
    and functional real world application. The Books Application deals with
    the user interface as well as the back end part of the application. This
    involves the database access and the implementation of business logic. The
    Books Application will lead you through everything it takes to get an
    actual application up and running with special focus on developing the SQL
    and data management layers of your application.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Learning Objectives Checklist</title>

      <para>At the end of this tutorial, you should be able to
      understand:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the NEF Application Directory Structure</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the NEF Project File</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>how to set up the sample application</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>use of NEF Starter Application</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>creation and testing of Data Layer</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>creation and testing of Presentation Layer</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  &__nef-assumptions__drd5ufsf;

  &__nef-starter-app-setup__dr4w0y2f;

  <section>
    <title>Key Concepts</title>

    <para>This section outlines some of the important, global concepts that
    you should be familiar with before embarking on developing your own
    applications.</para>

    &__nef-key-features__dr4qnp41;

    &__nef-project-file__dr4s5f91;

    &__web-file__dr4thoqz;
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Functionality</title>

    <para>The NEF Books Application is a small application meant to be used
    for a personal library of books. It allows you to track the books you have
    and add more books to your collection or edit information stored about
    existing books. It also allows you to search your collection for a
    particular book based on your own custom search criteria.</para>

    <para>The overall functionality of the application is limited but
    complete. As such it demonstrates a few of the main types of data
    manipulation that developers need to take care of in every application. In
    the end, the goal is to show you just how much power can be wielded with
    just a few lines of XML and Java code when armed with the strength of
    Sparx.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Design</title>

    <section>
      <title>Application Design</title>

      <para>The Books Application is designed around the basic Sparx
      components. It will use static SQL and associated reports to help you
      track the books stored in the application. Searches, on the other hand,
      require a dynamically generated SQL in the form of a Query
      Definition.</para>

      <para>The last aspect to take care of is the data storage. It is
      possible to use expensive abd overkill (in all certainty) database like
      Oracle for this application. Instead, the data storage of choice is the
      Java-based embedded database that is included in the Sparx Starter
      Application: <productname>HypersonicSQL</productname><footnote>
          <para>To learn more about <productname>HypersonicSQL, please go to
          <ulink
          url="http://hsqldb.sourceforge.net/">http://hsqldb.sourceforge.net/</ulink></productname></para>
        </footnote>. All the application components are included in the
      <filename>project.xml</filename> file for the Books Application.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Database Design</title>

      <para>The Books Application deals with books and only books. Therefore,
      the information that needs to be stored in the database will be about
      books. The four pieces of information that the Books Application will
      store for this example are its ID, name, author, genre and ISBN. Of
      these, the genre is the only one that can be common across multiple
      books. In database language, the genre (book type) has a one-to-many
      relationship with the books.<figure>
          <title>Basic E-R Diagram for Books Application Database</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-books-app-schema.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para>The figure shows the entity-relationship diagram for the data we
      will be using. The database for the Books Application will be designed
      to store each entity (and its attributes) in a separate table. As with
      the application design, the database design will become clearer when it
      is implemented later in this tutorial.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Renaming the Starter Application</title>

    <para>You can now build your Books Application upon the Starter
    Application's directory structure. Rename the Starter Application's root
    folder (<filename class="directory">nefs-starter-empty</filename>) to your
    application's name. This tutorial uses <filename
    class="directory">nefs-sample-books</filename> as the root folder name for
    the Books Application.</para>
  </section>

  &__nef-project-file-tags-descr__drcg7alc;

  <section>
    <title>Creating the Data Layer</title>

    <para>With the empty (Starter) application successfully created and
    running, it is time to work on the backbone of the Books Application: the
    database.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Setting up the Data Source</title>

      <para>To set up the Books Application database, you need to have a
      database connection (data source) pointing towards your database. This
      is accomplished by using the <sgmltag>connection-provider</sgmltag> tag
      in the Project File (<filename>project.xml</filename>). <example>
          <title>Setting up the Data Source for Books Application</title>

          <programlisting>&lt;project xmlns:xdm="http://www.netspective.org/Framework/Commons/XMLDataModel"&gt;
...

&lt;<emphasis>connection-provider</emphasis> <emphasis>
                 class="com.netspective.axiom.connection.JakartaCommonsDbcpConnectionProvider"</emphasis>&gt; <co
              id="declare-conn-provider-tags-eg-1" />

 &lt;<emphasis>data-source</emphasis> name="<emphasis>jdbc/default</emphasis>"&gt; <co
              id="declare-conn-provider-tags-eg-2" />
  &lt;<emphasis>driver-class</emphasis>&gt;org.hsqldb.jdbcDriver&lt;/driver-class&gt; <co
              id="declare-conn-provider-tags-eg-3" />
  &lt;<emphasis>url</emphasis>&gt;
  vs-expr:jdbc:hsqldb:${servlet-context-path:/WEB-INF/database/instance/db} <co
              id="declare-conn-provider-tags-eg-4" />
  &lt;/url&gt; 
  &lt;<emphasis>user</emphasis>&gt;sa&lt;/user&gt; <co
              id="declare-conn-provider-tags-eg-5" />
  &lt;<emphasis>password</emphasis>&gt;&lt;/password&gt; <co
              id="declare-conn-provider-tags-eg-6" />
 &lt;/data-source&gt;

&lt;/connection-provider&gt;</programlisting>
        </example><calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="declare-conn-provider-tags-eg-1">
            <para>A <sgmltag>connection-provider</sgmltag> tag is used to
            declare the connection to your application's database. <note>
                <para>Note that data sources specified under this connection
                provider will be managed by the Jakarta Commons DBCP. If you
                wish to use JNDI, you simply have to specify the resource
                according to the server you're using.</para>
              </note></para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-conn-provider-tags-eg-2">
            <para>Each <sgmltag>connection-provider</sgmltag> tag may contain
            one or more <sgmltag>data-source</sgmltag> tags. The
            <sgmltag>data-source</sgmltag> tag is used to specify the data
            source for the application. Any data source called
            '<emphasis>jdbc/default</emphasis>' is automatically used as the
            default JDBC data source. That is why the name of the data source
            in the above example code is set to "<literal>jdbc/default".
            </literal><note>
                <para>If you wish to change the name of the default data
                source, you may specify it in <filename>project.xml</filename>
                using the <sgmltag>default-data-source</sgmltag> tag.</para>
              </note></para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-conn-provider-tags-eg-3">
            <para>The <sgmltag>driver-class</sgmltag> tag is used to provide
            the driver to be used for the specified database. Since the Books
            Application uses HSQL database, our sample code specifies the
            appropriate JDBC driver.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-conn-provider-tags-eg-4">
            <para>The url is the JDBC URL used to connect to the database. The
            JDBC driver uses it to point to a specific database on a specific
            server. The URL has three parts which are separated by a colon
            "<literal>:</literal>". The first part is always
            "<literal>jdbc</literal>" and the second part is usually the name
            of the driver. In the example code, <literal>hsqldb</literal> is
            the name of the driver that is used to connect to your
            <productname>HypersonicSQL</productname> database. The third part
            is the name of the database.</para>

            <para>It is important to note the
            <sgmltag>servlet-context-path</sgmltag> value source. Value
            sources allow dynamic data to be included in XML without creating
            a programming language inside XML. In the example code, the
            <sgmltag>servlet-context-path</sgmltag> value source creates the
            database named '<literal>db</literal>' in <filename
            class="directory">WEB-INF</filename>/<filename
            class="directory">database</filename>/<filename
            class="directory">instance</filename> folder.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-conn-provider-tags-eg-5">
            <para>The <sgmltag>user</sgmltag> tag defines a default user to
            log in to the database. The example code specifies
            '<literal>sa</literal>' which is the default user for System
            Administrator.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-conn-provider-tags-eg-6">
            <para>The <sgmltag>password </sgmltag>tag is used to provide the
            password for the log in user. The default '<literal>sa</literal>'
            user has no password.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist><note>
          <para>Please see the NEF User's Manual or review Tag Documentation
          in the Console to get further details on the each tag.</para>
        </note></para>

      <para>The above sample code declares a data source for the Books
      Application database.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Unit Testing the Data Source</title>

        <para>You may test the data source by using <guimenu>Data
        Management</guimenu> | <guisubmenu>Data Sources</guisubmenu> section
        in the Console of your Books Application.</para>

        <para><screenshot>
            <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-datasource.gif" />
          </screenshot></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Schema</title>

      <para>After analyzing the information that needs to be stored in the
      database and judging from the E-R diagram shown earlier, you can derive
      the database schema that is necessary for the Books Application. It is a
      very simple schema consisting of only two tables:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Book Type</emphasis>: This table is used to store
          information aboout the different genres (types) of books.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Book Info</emphasis>: This table stores all the
          attributes of the books.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The two tables are 1:n related by the <literal>genre</literal> (in
      Book Info) and type (in Book Type) fields. Once entered as XML, this
      schema is available for platform-independent database access from your
      application.<note>
          <para>The entire schema, and the other larger and more complex ones
          that you might develop for enterprise applications, can be
          represented entirely in <filename>project.xml</filename> file of
          your application.</para>
        </note></para>

      <para>Following is the code that creates the Books Application
      schema:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Creating the Books Application Schema</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;<emphasis>schema</emphasis> name="db"&gt; <co
            id="declare-schema-tags-eg-1" />
  &lt;<emphasis>xdm:include resource="com/netspective/axiom/conf/schema.xml"</emphasis>/&gt; <co
            id="declare-schema-tags-eg-2" />

  &lt;<emphasis>table</emphasis> name="Book_Info" abbrev="bkI" <emphasis>type="Presentation"</emphasis>&gt; <co
            id="declare-schema-tags-eg-3" />
   &lt;<emphasis>column</emphasis> name="id" type="text" size="10" <emphasis>primary-key="yes"</emphasis> 
                     descr="Unique ID for every book in the database"/&gt; <co
            id="declare-schema-tags-eg-4" />
   &lt;column name="name" type="text" size="64" descr="Name of the book"/&gt;
   &lt;column name="author" type="text" size="64" descr="Name of the author(s)"/&gt;
   &lt;column name="genre" <emphasis>lookup-ref="Book_Type"</emphasis>/&gt; <co
            id="declare-schema-tags-eg-5" />
   &lt;column name="isbn" type="text" size="10" 
           <emphasis>unique="yes"</emphasis> descr="The 10 digit ISBN number"/&gt; <co
            id="declare-schema-tags-eg-6" />
  &lt;/table&gt;

  &lt;table name="Book_Type" abbrev="bkT" <emphasis>type="Enumeration"</emphasis>&gt; <co
            id="declare-schema-tags-eg-7" />
   <emphasis>&lt;enumerations&gt;</emphasis> <co id="declare-schema-tags-eg-8" />
    <emphasis>&lt;enum&gt;</emphasis>Science Fiction&lt;/enum&gt; 
    &lt;enum&gt;Mystery&lt;/enum&gt;
    &lt;enum&gt;Business&lt;/enum&gt;
    &lt;enum&gt;Information Technology&lt;/enum&gt;
    &lt;enum&gt;Nuclear Physics&lt;/enum&gt;
    &lt;enum&gt;Chemistry&lt;/enum&gt;
   &lt;/enumerations&gt;
  &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/schema&gt;</programlisting>

        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="declare-schema-tags-eg-1">
            <para>All schemas are declared using the <sgmltag
            class="starttag">schema</sgmltag> tag and are uniquely identified
            with a <sgmltag>name</sgmltag> (<literal>db</literal> in this
            case). You may define multiple schemas within the same
            project.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-schema-tags-eg-2">
            <para>The default
            <filename>com/netspective/axiom/conf/schema.xml</filename>
            resource file contains dozens of built-in data types and table
            types that may be extended or just used. Types such as
            <literal>text</literal>, <literal>integer</literal>,
            <literal>float</literal>, <literal>currency</literal>,
            <literal>date</literal>, and even composite types such as
            <literal>duration</literal> are built-into Axiom.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-schema-tags-eg-3">
            <para>Each schema may contain one or more <sgmltag>table</sgmltag>
            tags to define database tables. Each table has a
            <sgmltag>name</sgmltag> and <sgmltag>abbrev</sgmltag>(iation)
            attribute associated with it. The table also has a
            <sgmltag>type</sgmltag> attribute. Axiom supplies various built-in
            table types. The <sgmltag>type </sgmltag>attribute for the
            <literal>Book_Info</literal> table is set to
            '<sgmltag>presentation</sgmltag>' which gives it a default
            dialog.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-schema-tags-eg-4">
            <para>The <sgmltag>column</sgmltag> tag is used to define a field
            (column) in the table. Each column has <sgmltag>name</sgmltag>,
            <sgmltag>type</sgmltag>, <sgmltag>size</sgmltag> and
            <sgmltag>descr</sgmltag>(iption) attributes associated with it. To
            specify a field as the primary key of the table, set the
            <sgmltag>primary-key</sgmltag> attribute's value to
            '<literal>yes</literal>'.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-schema-tags-eg-5">
            <para>The <sgmltag>lookup-ref</sgmltag> attribute specifies a
            general foreign key relationship. The format is
            <varname>Table_X</varname>.<varname>Column_Y</varname>. This
            creates a 1:1 or 1:N relationship from the defining column which
            references the foreign <varname>Column_Y</varname> of
            <varname>Table_X</varname>. The example code only specifies the
            table name (<literal>Book_Type</literal>) for the
            <sgmltag>lookup-ref</sgmltag> attribute. This defines the foreign
            key relationship between the referncing column
            (<literal>genre</literal> in this case) and the primary key column
            (<literal>type</literal> in this case) of the referenced
            (<literal>Book_Type</literal>) table.<note>
                <para>If you use this attribute, the type attribute is not
                required. It is set to the same type as the referenced
                column.</para>
              </note></para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-schema-tags-eg-6">
            <para>The unique attribute specifies whether the column's values
            should be unique. This means that no two rows should share the
            same valuefor this column. When this value is set to 'yes', this
            attribute creates a unique index based on this single column.
            <note>
                <para>If more than one column need to be unique (as a
                composite), use the index child element of the table element
                to create a unique index based on multiple columns.</para>
              </note></para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-schema-tags-eg-7">
            <para>The second <sgmltag>table</sgmltag> tag block is used to
            define the <literal>Book Type</literal> table. This table is
            defined as an <sgmltag>Enumeration</sgmltag>. An
            <sgmltag>Enumeration</sgmltag> is a special type of table that is
            generated by Sparx. It consists of the following three fields per
            record:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><sgmltag>id</sgmltag>: contains a unique value which is
                used to relate the enumeration table in a 1:n manner with
                other tables</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><sgmltag>caption</sgmltag>: contains non-null value that
                is used to to provide a short description of each value in the
                enumeration</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><sgmltag>abbrev</sgmltag>: an optional field containing
                the abbreviation for the caption.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>The syntax of an enumeration table is unlike that of regular
            tables. However, once parsed and interpreted, enumeration tables
            are translated into a set of regular tables for relational
            integrity purposes.<note>
                <para>An enumeration table is used to established a 1:n
                relationship between an attribute of an object (e.g.
                <literal>genre</literal> of the book in this case) and the
                object itself (the <literal>book</literal> in this case). It
                does this by letting the <sgmltag>id</sgmltag> field of the
                attribute enumeration table be inserted as a foreign key in
                the table containing records for the object. In this
                particular scenario, the <sgmltag>lookup-ref</sgmltag>
                attribute of the <literal>genre</literal> field in the
                <literal>Book_Info </literal>table makes that happen.</para>
              </note></para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-schema-tags-eg-8">
            <para>Each enumeration type table contains an
            <sgmltag>enumerations</sgmltag> tag. The values for the
            enumeration table (book types in this case) are specified with the
            help of <sgmltag>enum</sgmltag> tag. Each value is enclose within
            <sgmltag>enum</sgmltag> and <sgmltag>/enum</sgmltag> tag.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
      </example>

      <section>
        <title>Unit Testing the Schema</title>

        <para>You may view the newly defined schema by using <guimenu>Data
        Management</guimenu> | <guisubmenu>Schemas</guisubmenu> section in the
        Console of your Books Application.</para>

        <para><screenshot>
            <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-schemas.gif" />
          </screenshot></para>

        <para>There is a list of all the tables contained in the schema. It
        should list a total of 4 tables, of which the most important to you
        are the ones you explicitly created: <literal>Book_Info</literal> and
        <literal>Book_Type</literal>. Click on the Book_Info table to see more
        details about it.</para>

        <para><screenshot>
            <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-tabledoc.gif" />
          </screenshot></para>

        <para>As you can see, the detailed view of the Book_Info tables gives
        a lot of information about the table and the information stored in it.
        For each field in the table, you can see its name, data type, actual
        SQL data type it was created as, whether it is a field referencing
        other fields (e.g. genre field in the Book _Info table) abd the
        index(es) deined on this table.</para>

        <para>You can view the details for the Book_Info and other tables in
        the same manner.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Generating Data Definition Language (DDL)</title>

      <para>The DDL representation of your schema consists of the actual
      commands that you need to issue to a database to create the tables you
      specified in the schema and to populate them with any static data (such
      as the one stored in enumeration tables) if necessary. These commands
      are DBMS-specific.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Using the Ant Build in Console</title>

        <para>To create the HSQL database and its DDL, you can use the
        <guimenu>Project</guimenu> |<guisubmenu> Ant Build</guisubmenu>
        section in the Console. In order to create the HSQL database, you must
        run the "<literal>create-database-hsqldb</literal>" target.</para>

        <note>
          <para>Please note that you need the initial-and-test-data.xml file
          in order to create the HSQL database using the Ant Build Script. See
          <xref linkend="desc-init-data" /></para>
        </note>

        <para><graphic
        fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-ant-build.gif" /></para>

        <para>This erases the existing default datasource (Hypersonic
        database), generates the SQL DDL for the default schema, loads the SQL
        DDL (effectively creating the Hypersonic SQL database) and finally
        loads the 'starter' from XML files using Sparx import from XML
        feature. The Console displays differemt messages during the HSQL
        database creation (as show below):</para>

        <para></para>

        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-create-hsql-db.gif" />
        </screenshot>

        <note>
          <para>Please note that this target should be executed anytime the
          default schema is modified.</para>
        </note>

        <para>With this final step completed, you should be ready to add,
        update, delete and query data from the database using the Sparx
        Library. To do that, however, you need a user interface that will
        allow you to manipulate data as well as query what is stored in the
        database.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Automating the HSQL Database Generation</title>

        <para>You may also edit the <filename>web.xml</filename> file to
        automatically create the database each time the servlet is run for the
        first time. to do this, you need to add a
        <sgmltag>--init-first-time-using-ant</sgmltag> servlet option in the
        Sparx navigation controller using the following steps:</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Open the APP_ROOT/WEB-INF/web.xml file and look for the
            following Code:</para>

            <programlisting>&lt;servlet&gt;
 &lt;servlet-name&gt;SparxNavigationController&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
 &lt;servlet-class&gt;
   com.netspective.sparx.navigate.NavigationControllerServlet
 &lt;/servlet-class&gt;
&lt;/servlet&gt;</programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Add the <sgmltag>init-param</sgmltag> tag to the above block
            of code. The resulting code will look like this:</para>

            <programlisting>&lt;servlet&gt; 
 &lt;servlet-name&gt;SparxNavigationController&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
 &lt;servlet-class&gt;
   com.netspective.sparx.navigate.NavigationControllerServlet
 &lt;/servlet-class&gt;
 &lt;init-param&gt; 
  &lt;param-name&gt;com.netspective.sparx.navigate.CONTROLLER_SERVLET_OPTIONS&lt;/param-name&gt;
  &lt;param-value&gt;
  --init-first-time-using-ant=/WEB-INF/sparx/conf/ant-build-project.xml:create-database-hsqldb 
  &lt;/param-value&gt;
 &lt;/init-param&gt;
&lt;/servlet&gt;</programlisting>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>The above approach works because when the navigation controller
        runs, it creates a file called
        <replaceable>APP_ROOT</replaceable>/<filename
        class="directory">WEB-INF</filename>/<filename
        class="directory">sparx</filename>/<filename
        class="directory">conf</filename>/<filename>execution.properties</filename>.
        This properties file contains the execution count of the servlet. If
        the execution count is less than one, the Ant file
        (<filename>ant-build-project.xml</filename>) and the target you
        requested (create-database-hsqldb) will be run.</para>

        <note>
          <para>This is the best method to create databases because it
          automatically creates the database the very first time the servlet
          is run. And, if you ever want the database recreated, you can simply
          erase the <filename>execution.properties</filename> file.</para>
        </note>
      </section>

      <section id="desc-init-data">
        <title>Populating the HSQL Database with Test Data</title>

        <para>You will need some test data to be stored in the Books
        Application database. This will provide you with some initial data to
        test your application with. You can load this test data using the
        <filename class="directory">WEB-INF</filename>/<filename
        class="directory">database</filename>/<filename
        class="directory">data</filename>/<filename>initial-and-test-data.xml</filename>
        and <filename>initial-and-test-data.xsl</filename> files.</para>

        <important>
          <para>The <filename>initial-and-test-data.xml</filename> file is
          necessary to create the HSQL database.</para>
        </important>

        <example>
          <title>Loading Initial Test Data into Book_Info Table</title>

          <programlisting>&lt;<emphasis>!DOCTYPE dal SYSTEM "../defn/db-import.dtd"</emphasis>&gt; <co
              id="declare-test-db-xml-eg-1" />

&lt;<emphasis>dal</emphasis>&gt; <co id="declare-test-db-xml-eg-2" />
    &lt;<emphasis>book-info</emphasis> <co id="declare-test-db-xml-eg-3" />
        id="test-001" name="Book 001"
        author="Smith, James R." genre="Science Fiction" isbn="test001"/&gt;

    &lt;book-info
        id="test-002" name="Book 002"
        author="Jones, Rober. J." genre="Mystery" isbn="test002"/&gt;

&lt;/dal&gt;</programlisting>

          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="declare-test-db-xml-eg-1">
              <para>The db-import.dtd is the DTD that is automatically created
              (by the Ant Build) based on the schema that is provided by the
              <sgmltag>schema</sgmltag> tag. The DTD is always called
              <replaceable>dbname</replaceable>-import.dtd, where
              <replaceable>dbname</replaceable> is the name specified in the
              <sgmltag>schema</sgmltag> tag.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-test-db-xml-eg-2">
              <para>The root tag for the initial-and-test-data.xml is
              <sgmltag>dal. </sgmltag></para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-test-db-xml-eg-3">
              <para>The root dal tag may contain one or more tags named as
              <replaceable>table-name
              </replaceable>(<literal>book-info</literal> in this case). Note
              that the underscore "<symbol>_</symbol>" in the original table
              name "<literal>book_info</literal>" (specified by
              <sgmltag>schema</sgmltag> tag in the project file) is replaced
              with a hyphen "<symbol>-</symbol>". The table field names become
              the attributes for the table-name tag (<sgmltag>id</sgmltag>,
              <sgmltag>name</sgmltag>, <sgmltag>author</sgmltag>,
              <sgmltag>genre</sgmltag> and <sgmltag>isbn</sgmltag> in this
              case). The values you provide for these fields are stored in the
              corresponding hsql table.</para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
        </example>

        <para>You may optionally use XSL to automate the creation of a large
        number of test data.</para>

        <example>
          <title>Using XSL to Generate Test Data</title>

          <programlisting>&lt;xsl:stylesheet xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" version="1.0"
     xmlns:dal="http://www.netspective.org/Framework/Axiom/DataAccessLayer"&gt; <co
              id="declare-test-db-xsl-eg-1" />

    &lt;xsl:output method="xml" indent="yes"/&gt; <co
              id="declare-test-db-xsl-eg-2" />

    &lt;xsl:template match="*"&gt; <co id="declare-test-db-xsl-eg-3" />
        &lt;xsl:copy&gt;
            &lt;xsl:copy-of select="attribute::*[. != '']"/&gt;
            &lt;xsl:apply-templates/&gt;
        &lt;/xsl:copy&gt;
    &lt;/xsl:template&gt;

    &lt;xsl:template match="generate-book-info-records"&gt; <co
              id="declare-test-db-xsl-eg-4" />
        &lt;xsl:call-template name="iterate-one"&gt; 
            &lt;xsl:with-param name="x"&gt;&lt;xsl:value-of select="@count"/&gt;&lt;/xsl:with-param&gt; 
        &lt;/xsl:call-template&gt;
    &lt;/xsl:template&gt;

    &lt;xsl:template name="iterate-one"&gt; <co id="declare-test-db-xsl-eg-5" />
        &lt;xsl:param name="x"/&gt; 

        &lt;book-info&gt; <co id="declare-test-db-xsl-eg-6" />
            &lt;xsl:attribute name="id"&gt;BOOK_&lt;xsl:value-of select="$x"/&gt;&lt;/xsl:attribute&gt; 
            &lt;xsl:attribute name="name"&gt;Book &lt;xsl:value-of select="$x"/&gt;&lt;/xsl:attribute&gt;
            &lt;xsl:attribute name="author"&gt;Author &lt;xsl:value-of select="$x"/&gt;&lt;/xsl:attribute&gt;
            &lt;xsl:attribute name="genre"&gt;Science Fiction&lt;/xsl:attribute&gt;
            &lt;xsl:attribute name="isbn"&gt;ISBN &lt;xsl:value-of select="$x"/&gt;&lt;/xsl:attribute&gt;
        &lt;/book-info&gt;

        &lt;xsl:if test="$x &gt; 1"&gt; <co id="declare-test-db-xsl-eg-7" />
            &lt;xsl:call-template name="iterate-one"&gt;
                &lt;xsl:with-param name="x" select="$x - 1"/&gt;
            &lt;/xsl:call-template&gt;
        &lt;/xsl:if&gt;
    &lt;/xsl:template&gt;

&lt;/xsl:stylesheet&gt;</programlisting>

          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="declare-test-db-xsl-eg-1">
              <para>Defining the Axiom Data Access Layer namespace prefix
              <sgmltag>dal</sgmltag>.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-test-db-xsl-eg-2">
              <para>Defines the output of the XSL (XML in this case).</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-test-db-xsl-eg-3">
              <para>Defines the default template.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-test-db-xsl-eg-4">
              <para>The template that you will use in your XML file. This
              template receives, through the parameter
              <varname>count</varname>, the number of records to be added. It
              calls another custom template named "iterate-one". The value of
              <varname>count</varname> parameter is also sent to the called
              template.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-test-db-xsl-eg-5">
              <para>This is the iterate-one template which is called by the
              generate-info-records template. It generates the values for all
              the fields of Book_Info table.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-test-db-xsl-eg-6">
              <para>The book-info XML records are generated using the value of
              parameter <varname>x</varname>, which changes on every iteration
              of the iterate-one template.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-test-db-xsl-eg-7">
              <para>This tag is responsible for recursively calling the
              iterate-one template. It checks the value of the parameter
              <varname>x</varname> and, if it is greater than 1, decreases it
              by one to call the iterate-one template with this new
              value.</para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
        </example>

        <para>This XSL can be incorporated in your XML file using the
        following code:</para>

        <example>
          <title>Incorporating XSL in the Test Data XSL</title>

          <programlisting>&lt;?transform --xslt initial-and-test-data.xsl?&gt; <co
              id="incorporate-xsl-eg-1" />
&lt;!DOCTYPE dal SYSTEM "../defn/db-import.dtd"&gt;
&lt;dal&gt;
    &lt;generate-book-info-records count="100"/&gt; <co
              id="incorporate-xsl-eg-2" />
&lt;/dal&gt;</programlisting>

          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="incorporate-xsl-eg-1">
              <para>The xdm-transform processing instruction tells Sparx to
              filter special tags through the XSLT before processing.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="incorporate-xsl-eg-2">
              <para>Calling the the template from XSL to generate 100 test
              records for Book_Info table.</para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
        </example>

        <note>
          <para>The XSL is optional. It is merely a way of automating the
          creation of lots of test data. You can manually create the XML and
          leave out the XSL.</para>
        </note>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>DDL and HSQL Database Files</title>

        <para>The DDL generation process creates the <filename
        class="directory">WEB-INF</filename>/<filename
        class="directory">database</filename> folder. This folder contains
        further sub-folders: <filename class="directory">defn</filename> and
        <filename class="directory">instance</filename>.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>defn</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This folder contains the SQL files containing
              DBMS-specific database creation scripts.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>instance</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This folder contains the HSQL database files:
              <filename>db.properties</filename>,
              <filename>db.script</filename>, <filename>db.data</filename> and
              <filename>db.backup</filename>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Unit Testing the HSQL Database</title>

        <para>You may test the newly created HSQL database through
        <guimenu>Data Management</guimenu> | <guisubmenu>Data
        Sources</guisubmenu> | <guimenuitem>SQL Explorer</guimenuitem> option
        in the Console. Enter a SQL query for the <literal>Book_Info</literal>
        table in the SQL Editor.</para>

        <para></para>

        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-sql-explorer.gif" />
        </screenshot>

        <para>To execute the test query, click the <command>OK
        </command>button. This displays the query result form (as shown
        below):</para>

        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-db-test-result.gif" />
        </screenshot>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Data Management Layer</title>

      <para>The Books Application uses two types of queries for data
      management:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Static SQL</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A static SQL statement is merely an encapsulation of a
            regular SQL statement within the XML definition required by Sparx
            to interpret it. Once defined, a single or multiple SQL statements
            may be used in reports, dialogs (forms), Servlets, templates, or
            JSP-pages. All the static SQL statements with the bind parameters
            are declared in the Books Application Project File.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Dynamic SQL (Query-Defn)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>One of Axiom's powerful features is to generate dynamic SQL
            statements based upon user input. The dynamic SQL generator can
            also generate different output formats such as pageable HTML
            reports with configurable rows per page or comma separated value
            (CSV) reports. The main component of the dynamic queries is the
            query definition dialog which is used to define bind parameters of
            the dynamic SQL statement. Thus, the dynamic query generator can
            be thought of as a combination of Dialog and Static Query
            features.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <note>
        <para>All the static and dynamic SQL statements are declared in the
        Books Application Project File
        (<filename>project.xml</filename>)</para>
      </note>

      <section id="section-declare-static-qry">
        <title>Declaring a Static Query</title>

        <para>The Books Application uses a simple join query to get
        information about all the books and their genres. Following is the xml
        declaration that performs this task:</para>

        <example>
          <title>Declaring a Static Query</title>

          <programlisting>&lt;<emphasis>queries</emphasis> package="books"&gt; <co
              id="declare-static-sql-tags-eg-1" />

 &lt;<emphasis>query</emphasis> name="get-all-books"&gt; <co
              id="declare-static-sql-tags-eg-2" />
  select id, name, author, book_type.caption, isbn <co
              id="declare-static-sql-tags-eg-3" />
         from book_info, book_type
         where genre = book_type.id
 &lt;/query&gt;

&lt;/queries&gt;</programlisting>

          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="declare-static-sql-tags-eg-1">
              <para>All the static in Axiom must belong to a statement package
              represented by <sgmltag>queries</sgmltag> XML tag. The statement
              package is identified by its name (<literal>books</literal> in
              the above example). You can define multiple packages within your
              application's project.xml file.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-static-sql-tags-eg-2">
              <para>A static query is defined (with or without bind
              parameters) by using the <sgmltag>query</sgmltag> tag. Each
              query is identified by its name
              (<literal>get-all-books</literal> in the above example). <note>
                  <para>The namespace of a query is always
                  <replaceable>queryPkg</replaceable>.<replaceable>queryName</replaceable>.
                  This means you can have more than one queries with same name
                  if each of them belongs to a different query package.</para>
                </note></para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-static-sql-tags-eg-3">
              <para>The static SQL (with or without bind parameters) is
              declared under the query tag. The query in this example declares
              a join on the <literal>Book_Type</literal> and
              <literal>Book_Info</literal> tables using the
              <literal>genre</literal> (from <literal>Book_Info</literal>) and
              <literal>id</literal> (from <literal>Book_Type</literal>)
              fields.</para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Presenting the Results of a Static Query</title>

        <para>The next step is to define the customized way of displaying the
        result of your <literal>get-all-books</literal> query.</para>

        <example>
          <title>Presenting the Results of a Static Query</title>

          <programlisting>&lt;queries package="books"&gt; 

 &lt;query name="get-all-books"&gt; 
  select id, name, author, book_type.caption, isbn 
         from book_info, book_type
         where genre = book_type.id

  &lt;<emphasis>presentation</emphasis>&gt; <co id="declare-pres-tags-eg-1" />
    &lt;<emphasis>panel</emphasis> name="main" height="300"&gt; <co
              id="declare-pres-tags-eg-2" />
        &lt;<emphasis>frame</emphasis> heading="<emphasis>static:All available books</emphasis>"/&gt; <co
              id="declare-pres-tags-eg-3" />
        &lt;<emphasis>report</emphasis>&gt; <co id="declare-pres-tags-eg-4" />
           &lt;<emphasis>actions</emphasis>&gt; <co
              id="declare-pres-tags-eg-5" />
               &lt;<emphasis>action</emphasis> <emphasis>type="add"</emphasis> caption="Add Book" redirect="page-id:/add"/&gt; <co
              id="declare-pres-tags-eg-6" />
               &lt;action type="<emphasis><literal>edit</literal></emphasis>" <emphasis>redirect</emphasis>="page-id:/edit?id=<emphasis>${0}</emphasis>"/&gt; <co
              id="declare-pres-tags-eg-7" />
               &lt;action type="<emphasis>delete</emphasis>" redirect="page-id:/delete?id=${0}"/&gt; <co
              id="declare-pres-tags-eg-8" />
           &lt;/actions&gt;
           &lt;column heading="ID" format="plain" redirect="page-id:/edit?id=${0}"/&gt; <co
              id="declare-pres-tags-eg-9" />
           &lt;column heading="Name" /&gt;
           &lt;column heading="Author"/&gt;
           &lt;column heading="Genre"/&gt;
           &lt;column heading="ISBN"/&gt;
        &lt;/report&gt;
    &lt;/panel&gt;
  &lt;/presentation&gt;
 &lt;/query&gt;

&lt;/queries&gt;</programlisting>

          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="declare-pres-tags-eg-1">
              <para>Each <sgmltag>query</sgmltag> tag contains a
              <sgmltag>presentation </sgmltag>tag associated with it. This tag
              defines presentation aspects of the query.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-pres-tags-eg-2">
              <para>The panel tag is used to display a panel of given height.
              This panel serves as a container for the displayed query
              result.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-pres-tags-eg-3">
              <para>The frame tag defines a frame to be drawn around the query
              result. The heading attribute is assigned a value using static
              value source.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-pres-tags-eg-4">
              <para>A report is a way to customize the output of a SQL
              statement on the page.</para>

              <note>
                <para>Each SQL statement may have any number of
                <sgmltag>report</sgmltag> tags as necessary. That way, a
                single statement can be viewed differently depending upon what
                context itâ€™s being called in.</para>
              </note>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-pres-tags-eg-5">
              <para>You can declare a set of actions for your query's result.
              This is done using the <sgmltag>actions</sgmltag> tag. These
              actions provide a way to perform different functions on the
              displayed query result. Sparx has pre-defined action types for
              performing add, edit and delete operations on the selected
              record within your query result.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-pres-tags-eg-6">
              <para>The action tag is used to define individual actions
              (<literal>add</literal> in this case). The
              <sgmltag>action</sgmltag> tag may specify a <sgmltag
              class="attribute">redirect</sgmltag> attribute to automatically
              redirect to another page whenever it is chosen. The name of the
              redirect page is supplied using the <sgmltag>page-id</sgmltag>
              value source.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-pres-tags-eg-7">
              <para>Declaring <literal>edit</literal> action. You may also
              supply parameters and their values within the redirect URL
              (selected record's <literal>id</literal> field in this case).
              </para>

              <para>Any ${XXX} specifies a dynamic replacement. Usually, value
              sources are used within the brackets but when the dynamic
              replacement definition is used within a report definition
              (declared using <sgmltag>report</sgmltag> tag), you can insert a
              number within the brackets to indicate the column index of the
              report. In the above example, <emphasis>${0}</emphasis> is used
              to indicate that it should be replaced with the value of the
              first column of current row.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-pres-tags-eg-8">
              <para>Declaring the <literal>delete</literal> action with
              redirect attribute pointing to the <literal>delete</literal>
              page.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-pres-tags-eg-9">
              <para>Every SQL report contains <sgmltag>column</sgmltag> tags
              that are used to customize the appearance of a particular column
              or, more accurately, a particular field. You may also specify a
              redirect page URL (<literal>edit</literal> page in this
              case).</para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Unit Testing a Static SQL</title>

        <para>To test your newly defined static query, go to the <guimenu>Data
        Management</guimenu> | <guisubmenu>Static Queries</guisubmenu> section
        in the Console. This displays all the Static SQL statements defined in
        your <filename>project.xml</filename> file.</para>

        <para><screenshot>
            <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-static-queries.gif" />
          </screenshot></para>

        <para>Click on the <literal>get-all-books</literal> query to see the
        SQL statement.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console--static-qry-doc.gif" />
        </screenshot>

        <para>Click on the <guimenuitem>Unit Test</guimenuitem> option in the
        left menu bar. The unit test page is displayed containing a
        form/dialog for specifying the number of record rows to be displayed
        per page. By default, the number of records displayed per page is 10
        records per page. Enter the new value in this field if you want to
        change the number of records displayed per page. Click the
        <command>OK</command> button. The query is executed and its result is
        displayed (as shown below).</para>

        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-static-qry-unit-test.gif" />
        </screenshot>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title id="section-declare-dynamic-qry">Declaring a Dynamic Query
        (Query Definition)</title>

        <para>Query definitions are one of the most powerful features that
        Sparx provides developers. Using query definitions a developer wields
        extreme flexibility and power with an ease rivaled by few, if any,
        other components of Sparx.</para>

        <para>The Books Application will make use of the following query
        definition:</para>

        <example>
          <title>Declaring a Dynamic Query (query Definition)</title>

          <programlisting>&lt;<emphasis>query-defn</emphasis> name="books"&gt; <co
              id="declare-qry-defn-tags-eg-1" />
  &lt;<emphasis>field</emphasis> name="book_id" caption="Book ID" <emphasis>join</emphasis>="BookInfo" column="id"/&gt; <co
              id="declare-qry-defn-tags-eg-2" />
  &lt;field name="name" caption="Name" join="BookInfo" column="name"/&gt; 
  &lt;field name="author" caption="Author" join="BookInfo" column="author"/&gt;
  &lt;field <emphasis>name="genre_id"</emphasis> caption="Genre ID" join="BookInfo" <emphasis>column="genre"</emphasis>/&gt; <co
              id="declare-qry-defn-tags-eg-3" />
  &lt;field name="genre_caption" caption="Genre" join="BookType" column="caption"/&gt;
  &lt;field name="isbn" caption="ISBN" join="BookInfo" column="isbn"/&gt;

  &lt;join name="BookInfo" table="book_info"/&gt; 
  <emphasis>&lt;join name="BookType" table="book_type" condition="BookType.id = BookInfo.genre"/&gt;</emphasis> <co
              id="declare-qry-defn-tags-eg-4" />

&lt;/query-defn&gt;</programlisting>

          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-tags-eg-1">
              <para>All query definitions are declared using the
              <sgmltag>query-defn</sgmltag> tag and are uniquely identified
              with a name (<literal>books</literal> in this case).</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-tags-eg-2">
              <para>Each query definition contains one ore more
              <sgmltag>field</sgmltag> tags that declare the selectable
              fields. The <sgmltag>field</sgmltag> tags are specified so that
              Axiom knows what fields the user should be allowed to select.
              Query definition fields may come from a mix of tables so long as
              they have appropriately defined <sgmltag>join</sgmltag>
              attribute values. The value of the <sgmltag>join</sgmltag>
              attribute is a reference to a <sgmltag>join</sgmltag> tag later
              on in the query definition (<literal>BookInfo</literal> and
              <literal>bookType</literal> in this case).</para>

              <note>
                <para>In the context of the final SQL statement that Sparx
                generates, the field tags become a part of the select clause.
                i.e. the part of a select statement that determines which
                fields need to be returned.</para>
              </note>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-tags-eg-3">
              <para>The <sgmltag>column</sgmltag> attribute of <sgmltag>field
              </sgmltag>tag contains the field name (<literal>name</literal>
              in this case) as defined in the schema table
              (<literal>Book_Info</literal> in this case). The
              <sgmltag>name</sgmltag> attribute is used to define a different
              name for the schema table field (<literal>genre_id</literal> and
              <literal>genre</literal>, respectively, in this case).</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-tags-eg-4">
              <para>The <sgmltag>join</sgmltag> tag is used to let the query
              definition know of the list of tables and joins. This is
              necessary to be able to get all the fields that are a part of
              the query definition. Each <sgmltag>join</sgmltag> tag is
              uniquely identified through its name. The
              <sgmltag>table</sgmltag> attribute contains the schema table
              name whereas the <sgmltag>condition</sgmltag> attribute defines
              the join condition.</para>

              <note>
                <para>In the context of the final SQL statement that Sparx
                generates, the join tags become a part of the where clause to
                signify the relationships between tables (if any
                exists).</para>
              </note>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section id="desc-pres-dyn-qry">
        <title>Presenting the Results of a Dynamic Query (Query
        Definition)</title>

        <para>After defining the basic join on Books Application tables, the
        next step is to define the search dialog and the presentation of the
        search result. This is handled through the use of
        <sgmltag>presentation</sgmltag> tag and its child tags under
        <sgmltag>query-defn</sgmltag> tag.</para>

        <example>
          <title>Declaring the Search Dialog and Query Result
          Presentation</title>

          <programlisting>&lt;query-defn name="books"&gt;

 &lt;<emphasis>presentation</emphasis>&gt; <co
              id="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-1" />
   &lt;<emphasis>select-dialog</emphasis> name="searchBooksDialog" <emphasis>allow-debug</emphasis>="yes" <co
              id="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-2" />
                  <emphasis>hide-output-dests</emphasis>="no" <emphasis>hide-readonly-hints</emphasis>="yes" &gt; <emphasis>     
                  </emphasis> 
     &lt;<emphasis>frame</emphasis> heading="Search for Books" /&gt; <co
              id="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-3" />
     &lt;field type="text" name="book_id" caption="Book ID" /&gt;
     &lt;field type="text" name="name" caption="Book Name"/&gt;
     &lt;field type="text" name="author" caption="Author"/&gt;
     &lt;field type="text" name="isbn" caption="ISBN"/&gt;
     &lt;<emphasis>field</emphasis> type="select" style="list" name="genre" 
                          caption="Genre" choices="<emphasis>schema-enum:Book_Type</emphasis>"/&gt; <co
              id="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-4" />

     &lt;<emphasis>select</emphasis> name="test"&gt; <co
              id="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-5" />
        &lt;display field="book_id"/&gt; 
        &lt;display field="name"/&gt;
        &lt;display field="author"/&gt;
        &lt;<emphasis>display</emphasis> field="genre_caption"/&gt; <co
              id="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-6" />
        &lt;display field="isbn"/&gt;<emphasis>

        &lt;condition field="book_id" allow-null="no" comparison="equals" </emphasis><co
              id="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-7" />
                                   <emphasis>value</emphasis>="field" <emphasis>connector</emphasis>="and"/&gt; 
        &lt;condition field="name" allow-null="no" comparison="starts-with" 
                                   value="field:name" connector="and"/&gt;
        &lt;condition field="author" allow-null="no" comparison="equals" 
                                   value="field:author" connector="and"/&gt;
        &lt;condition field="genre_id" allow-null="no" comparison="equals" 
                                   value="field:genre" connector="and"/&gt;

        &lt;<emphasis>presentation</emphasis>&gt; <co
              id="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-8" />
           &lt;<emphasis>panel</emphasis> name="report"&gt; 
              &lt;frame heading="static:Book Search Results"/&gt;
                &lt;<emphasis>report</emphasis>&gt; <co
              id="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-9" />
                   &lt;<emphasis>column</emphasis> heading="ID" format="plain" <emphasis>redirect</emphasis>="page-id:/edit?id=${0}"/&gt; <co
              id="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-10" />
                   &lt;column heading="Name" /&gt;
                   &lt;column heading="Author"/&gt;
                   &lt;column heading="Genre"/&gt;
                   &lt;column heading="ISBN"/&gt;
                &lt;/report&gt;
             &lt;/panel&gt;
        &lt;/presentation&gt;
     &lt;/select&gt;
   &lt;/select-dialog&gt;
 &lt;/presentation&gt;
&lt;/query-defn&gt;</programlisting>

          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-1">
              <para>The search dialog and search field results are declared
              under a <sgmltag>presentation</sgmltag> tag in the
              <sgmltag>query-defn</sgmltag> hierarchy.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-2">
              <para>The <sgmltag>select-dialog</sgmltag> tag is essentially a
              dialog embedded inside a query definition. The purpose of this
              dialog is to provide a user interface for the query definition.
              Each select-dialog is uniquely identified through its
              name.</para>

              <note>
                <para>One query definition can have multiple
                <sgmltag>select-dialogs</sgmltag> declarations.</para>
              </note>

              <para>The <sgmltag>allow-debug</sgmltag> attribute of
              <sgmltag>select-dialog</sgmltag> tag is used to specify the
              query debug option. If it is set to "<literal>yes</literal>" (as
              in this example), a debug check box is displayed (with the
              caption <emphasis>View Generated SQL</emphasis>). When this
              checkbox is checked and the dialog is submitted, the generated
              SQL with its bind parameters is displayed for debugging purposes
              instead of execution of the generated SQL</para>

              <para>The <sgmltag>hide-output-dests</sgmltag> attribute is used
              to give the user several output options: HTML output (pageable
              report and row count per page), CSV output format, tab delimited
              format. This is done by setting the value of this attribute to
              "no". The <sgmltag>hide-readonly-hints</sgmltag> attribute is
              used to show or hide the field hints (as is the case in this
              example).</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-3">
              <para>The <sgmltag>frame</sgmltag> tag is used to draw a frame,
              with appropriate heading, around the search dialog.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-4">
              <para>The first part of a <sgmltag>select-dialog</sgmltag> is a
              declaration of all the fields (and their corresponding UI
              representations) that the <sgmltag>select-dialog</sgmltag> will
              use for user input. Each field has associated
              <sgmltag>name</sgmltag> and <sgmltag>caption</sgmltag>
              attributes. The <literal>genre</literal> field is declared to be
              a "<sgmltag>select</sgmltag>". The choices for this field are
              populated with the values from <literal>Book_Type</literal>
              table using <sgmltag>schema-enum</sgmltag> value source.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-5">
              <para>The second part of a <sgmltag>select-dialog</sgmltag> is a
              select section which has two parts in itself. The
              <sgmltag>select</sgmltag> component is what determines which of
              the select-dialogâ€™s declared fields are actually displayed in
              the dialog for this select-dialog. It also determines how each
              field will be interpreted by the query definition engine once
              the dialog is submitted. The select tag is uniquely identified
              through its name (<literal>test</literal> in this case).</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-6">
              <para>The <sgmltag>display</sgmltag> tags have one attribute,
              <sgmltag>field</sgmltag>, which points to the name of a field
              declared in the main query definition.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-7">
              <para>The <sgmltag>condition</sgmltag> tags determine how the
              data input from the <sgmltag>select-dialog</sgmltag> will be
              interpreted by the query definition engine. Basically, it
              defines the search criteria.</para>

              <para>Each condition tag represents a condition on a field
              specified by the <sgmltag>field</sgmltag> attribute. The
              <sgmltag>allow-null</sgmltag> attribute of the
              <sgmltag>condition</sgmltag> tag determines the behavior of the
              query definition engine if this field is left empty when the
              dialog is submitted. The value of this attribute is set to
              â€œ<literal>no</literal>â€ in this case. That is why the select
              generated will omit the field if the corresponding dialog field
              happens to be empty. The <sgmltag>comparison</sgmltag> attribute
              of the <sgmltag>condition</sgmltag> tag describes the relational
              operator to use ("<emphasis>equals</emphasis>" in this
              case).</para>

              <para>The <sgmltag>value</sgmltag> attribute of the
              <sgmltag>condition</sgmltag> tag describes the field from the
              main query definition (<literal>book_id</literal> in this case)
              with which this <sgmltag>select-dialog</sgmltag> field
              (<literal>book_id</literal> in this case) is to be compared. The
              select-dialog field is mentioned using the
              <sgmltag>field</sgmltag> value source.</para>

              <para>The <sgmltag>connector</sgmltag> attribute determines how
              many field criteria each record in the database has to match
              before it is selected. In this example, all the fields have a
              connector value of â€œ<sgmltag>and</sgmltag>â€ thus specifying that
              a record would have to match all the field criteria to be
              selected in the final result.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-8">
              <para>The result of this dynamically generated and executed
              query can be configured in different ways using
              <sgmltag>presentation</sgmltag> tag hierarchy.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-9">
              <para>The <sgmltag>report</sgmltag> tag customizes the displayed
              query result fields.</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-pres-tags-eg-10">
              <para>Each <sgmltag>report</sgmltag> tag contains
              <sgmltag>column</sgmltag> tags to customize the display of
              individual query result fields. You may also provide a redirect
              URL which a column through the <sgmltag>redirect</sgmltag>
              attribute. In this example, the <literal>ID</literal> field of
              the book record in the displayed result points to the
              <literal>Edit Book</literal> page. Clicking on this link will
              open the <literal>Edit Book</literal> page with the dialog
              fields populated with the selected book's information.</para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Unit Testing a Query Definition</title>

        <para>To test your newly defined static query, go to the <guimenu>Data
        Management</guimenu> | <guisubmenu>Dynamic Queries</guisubmenu>
        section in the Console. This displays all the Dynamic SQL statements
        defined in your <filename>project.xml</filename> file.</para>

        <para></para>

        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console--dynamic-queries.gif" />
        </screenshot>

        <para>Click on the <literal>books</literal> query to see the details
        of the query in a tabular form.</para>

        <para></para>

        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console--dynamic-qry-doc.gif" />
        </screenshot>

        <para>Click on the <guimenuitem>Unit Test</guimenuitem> option in the
        left menu bar. [TODO: Documentation to be made available when the
        Dynamic Query Unit Test option is functional]</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Creating the Presentation Layer</title>

    <para>The presentation layer of your Books Application comprises the
    following pages:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Home Page</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Add Books Page</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Edit Books Page</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Delete Books Page</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Search Books Page</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Console Page</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NEFS Sample Apps Home Page</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Home Page</title>

      <para>Your Books Application Home page will display list of all the
      books. It will also provide Edit and Delete options for each of the
      displayed books.</para>

      <para>Sparx handles the pages that an end user sees and the transfer of
      control from one page to another using URIs and URLs. This is called
      <literal>navigation</literal>. Once declared using XML, Sparx can
      automatically manage the visual and operational end-user control of the
      navigation from one area of your application to another. You simply
      define the rules for what happens when a user visits a page and Sparx
      takes care of the rest.</para>

      <para>Following is the XML declaration for your Books Application
      navigation:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Creating "Home" Page</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;project xmlns:xdm="http://www.netspective.org/Framework/Commons/XMLDataModel"&gt;
...
 &lt;<emphasis>navigation-tree</emphasis> name="app" <emphasis>default="yes"</emphasis>&gt; <co
            id="declare-nav-tags-eg-1" />
    &lt;<emphasis>page</emphasis> name="home" <emphasis>default="yes"</emphasis> caption="Home" <co
            id="declare-nav-tags-eg-2" />
          <emphasis>command="query,books.get-all-books,-,-,-,record-editor-compressed"</emphasis>/&gt; <co
            id="declare-nav-tags-eg-3" />
 &lt;/navigation-tree&gt;
...</programlisting>

        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="declare-nav-tags-eg-1">
            <para>The <sgmltag>navigation-tree</sgmltag> tag starts out the
            definition and appears as a child of the
            <sgmltag>project</sgmltag> tag. Each tree has a
            <sgmltag>name</sgmltag> (<literal>app</literal> in this case). The
            <sgmltag>name</sgmltag> attribute is required and must be unique
            across all navigation trees. The <sgmltag>caption</sgmltag>
            attribute is a value source and is always required. A tree may be
            marked with <sgmltag class="attribute">default</sgmltag>=<sgmltag
            class="attvalue">yes</sgmltag> if it is to be the default tree.
            Which tree is actually used by the application may be specfied as
            a servet parameter or chosen dynamically at runtime based on some
            processing rules. There is only one instance of each navigation
            tree that you define and the definition is shared across all users
            and threads.</para>

            <note>
              <para>You may declare as many navigation trees as your
              application needs.</para>
            </note>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-nav-tags-eg-2">
            <para>The <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag begins a definition of a
            single page and appears under the
            <sgmltag>navigation-tree</sgmltag> tag. Each page has a
            <sgmltag>name</sgmltag> (<literal>home</literal> in this case).
            The <sgmltag>name</sgmltag> attribute is required and must be
            unique within the navigation tree in which it is defined. A tree
            may be marked with <sgmltag
            class="attribute">default</sgmltag>=<sgmltag
            class="attvalue">yes</sgmltag> if it is to be the default tree.
            Which page is actually used by the application may be specfied as
            a servlet parameter or chosen dynamically at runtime based on some
            processing rules. There is only one instance of each page that you
            define and the definition is shared across all users and
            threads.</para>

            <note>
              <para>You may declare as many pages under a navigation-tree as
              your application needs.</para>
            </note>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-nav-tags-eg-3">
            <para>The page <sgmltag>command</sgmltag> attribute calls
            <methodname>execute</methodname>() on an instance of the
            <interfacename>com.netspective.sparx.command.Command</interfacename>
            interface and includes the content of the execution as the content
            of the page. The command attribute in this example executes the
            <sgmltag>query</sgmltag> <literal>get-all-books</literal> from the
            query package named <literal>books</literal> (see <xref
            linkend="section-declare-static-qry" />). It also specifies one of
            the pre-defined report skins
            (<sgmltag>record-editor-compressed</sgmltag> in this case) for the
            displayed report.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Add Book Page</title>

      <para>The next step is to create a page for adding books information to
      your database. This is achieved through the following XML
      declaration:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Creating "Add Book" Page</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;navigation-tree name="app" default="yes"&gt; 
  &lt;page name="add" caption="Add Book" <emphasis>command="dialog,schema.db.Book_Info,add"</emphasis>/&gt; <co
            id="declare-page-tags-eg-1" />
&lt;navigation-tree&gt;</programlisting>

        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="declare-page-tags-eg-1">
            <para>The <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag in the example code defines
            Books Application's <literal>Add Book</literal> page. The
            <sgmltag>command</sgmltag> attribute in this example displays and
            executes a dialog box for <literal>Book Info</literal> table using
            the "<sgmltag>add</sgmltag>" perspective.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Edit Book Page</title>

      <para>Your books application requires a way to edit the book information
      already stored in the database. For that, you will need an <literal>Edit
      Book</literal> page. This is achieved through the following XML
      declaration::</para>

      <example>
        <title>Creating "Edit Book" Page</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;navigation-tree name="app" default="yes"&gt;         
  &lt;page name="edit" caption="Edit Book" command="dialog,schema.db.Book_Info,<emphasis>edit</emphasis>" <co
            id="declare-edit-page-eg-1" />
        require-request-param="id" <co id="declare-edit-page-eg-2" />
        retain-params="id"&gt; <co id="declare-edit-page-eg-3" />
   &lt;missing-params-body&gt; <co id="declare-edit-page-eg-4" />
    Please choose a book to edit from the &amp;lt;a href='home'&amp;gt; books list&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. 
   &lt;/missing-params-body&gt;
  &lt;/page&gt;
&lt;/navigation-tree&gt;</programlisting>

        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="declare-edit-page-eg-1">
            <para>The <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag declares the <literal>Edit
            Book</literal> page. The <sgmltag>command</sgmltag> attribute
            displays and execute a dialog box for <literal>Book Info
            </literal>table using the "<sgmltag>edit</sgmltag>"
            perspective.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-edit-page-eg-2">
            <para>The <sgmltag>require-request-parameter</sgmltag> attribute
            specifies <varname>id</varname> as the required request parameter.
            The <varname>id</varname> parameter contains unique identifier for
            the book record that is being edited.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-edit-page-eg-3">
            <para>The <sgmltag>retain-params</sgmltag> attribute allows you to
            carry parameters from one page to another. In this example, the
            "id" parameter's value will be sent to anothe page (tab) when that
            tab/page is clicked.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-edit-page-eg-4">
            <para>The <sgmltag>missing-params-body</sgmltag> tag is used to
            optionally produce automatic error message when required request
            parameter <varname>('id'</varname> in this case) is not
            provided.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Delete Book Page</title>

      <para>The Delete Book page is declared through the following XML:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Creating "Delete Book" Page</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;navigation-tree name="app" default="yes"&gt;         
    &lt;page name="delete" caption="Delete Book" command="dialog,schema.db.Book_Info,<emphasis>delete</emphasis>" <co
            id="declare-delete-page-eg-1" />
          require-request-param="id" <co id="declare-delete-page-eg-2" />
          retain-params="id"&gt; <co id="declare-delete-page-eg-3" />
        &lt;missing-params-body&gt; <co id="declare-delete-page-eg-4" />
           Please choose a book to delete from the &amp;lt;a href='home'&amp;gt; books list&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.
        &lt;/missing-params-body&gt;
    &lt;/page&gt;
&lt;/navigation-tree&gt;</programlisting>

        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="declare-delete-page-eg-1">
            <para>The <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag declares the <literal>Delete
            Book</literal> page. The <sgmltag>command</sgmltag> attribute
            displays and execute a dialog box for <literal>Book Info</literal>
            table using the "<sgmltag>delete</sgmltag>" perspective.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-delete-page-eg-2">
            <para>The <sgmltag>require-request-parameter</sgmltag> attribute
            specifies <varname>id</varname> as the required request parameter.
            The <varname>id</varname> parameter contains unique identifier for
            the book record that is being deleted.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-delete-page-eg-3">
            <para>The <sgmltag>retain-params</sgmltag> attribute allows you to
            carry parameters from one page to another. In this example, the
            "id" parameter's value will be sent to anothe page (tab) when that
            tab/page is clicked.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-delete-page-eg-4">
            <para>The missing-params-body tag is used to optionally produce
            automatic error message when required request parameter
            <varname>('id'</varname> in this case) is not provided.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Search Books Page</title>

      <para>The Books Application has, at the moment, most of the
      functionality originally intended for it. The only bit of functionality
      that is left is that of being able to search for books matching any
      criteria the user chooses. For a small collection, the result of the
      <literal>get-all-books</literal> query is small enough to browse
      manually for the information pertaining to a book. For larger numbers of
      books, the power of a query definition can come in very handy to search
      the database for all books matching any criteria specified by the end
      user.</para>

      <para>The following XML declaration defines the <literal>Search
      Books</literal> page:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Creating "Search Books" Page</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;navigation-tree name="app" default="yes"&gt;         
   &lt;page name="search" caption="Search Books" 
                       command="query-defn, books, test, searchBooksDialog"/&gt; <co
            id="declare-qry-defn-use-eg-1" />
&lt;/navigation-tree&gt;</programlisting>

        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="declare-qry-defn-use-eg-1">
            <para>The page tag is used to declare the <literal>Search
            Books</literal> page. The command attribute uses the "query-defn"
            value source to display the search dialog and the query results.
            The example declaration specifies the
            <sgmltag>query-defn</sgmltag> named <literal>books</literal>. The
            select statement being used for creating the search criteria is
            <literal>test</literal> while the customization of query result is
            done by the <sgmltag>select-dialog</sgmltag> named
            <literal>searchBooksDialog</literal>.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Console Page</title>

      <para>Like every other Sparx application, your Books Application also
      has an associated Console. You may provide the access to this Console
      using the following XML declaration:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Linking to the Books Application Console</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;navigation-tree name="app" default="yes"&gt;  
 &lt;page name="console" caption="Console" redirect="servlet-context-uri:/console"/&gt; <co
            id="declare-console-eg-1" />
&lt;/navigation-tree&gt;</programlisting>

        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="declare-console-eg-1">
            <para>The <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag declares <literal>Cosole
            </literal>page for the <literal>Books Application</literal>. The
            <sgmltag>redirect</sgmltag> attribute is set (using the
            <sgmltag>servlet-context-uri</sgmltag> value source) to
            automatically redirect to the application Console.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Sample Apps Home Page</title>

      <para>As a last step to the creation of your Books Application, you will
      add a Sample Apps Home page using the following XML declaration:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Creating Sample Apps Home Page for Books Application</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;navigation-tree name="app" default="yes"&gt;  
   &lt;page name="sample-apps-home" caption="Sample Apps Home" <co
            id="declare-nefs-sample-apps-eg-1" />
                                 redirect="<emphasis>netspective-url:nefs-sample-apps-home</emphasis>"/&gt; 
&lt;/navigation-tree&gt;</programlisting>

        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="declare-nefs-sample-apps-eg-1">
            <para>The <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag declares the <literal>Sample
            Apps Home </literal>page. The <sgmltag>redirect</sgmltag>
            attribute specifies the URL of the Netspective <literal>Sample
            Apps</literal> page using the <sgmltag>netspective-url</sgmltag>
            value source.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Custom-Handling of Dialog's Next Action</title>

      <para>You may implement the Sparx
      <interfacename>DialogNextActionProvider</interfacename> interface to
      customize what happens after your Books Application's dialogs (forms)
      are submitted. In this example, you will try to send the dialogs (forms)
      back to the Books Application Home page. Following is the Java class
      (<classname>Util.java</classname>) that provides this functionality.
      This Java file will be saved in the <filename
      class="directory">WEB-INF</filename>/<filename
      class="directory">classes</filename>/<filename
      class="directory">app</filename> folder along with its class
      file.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Class for Custom-Handling of Dialog's Next Action</title>

        <programlisting>package app; <co id="util-class-eg-1" />

import com.netspective.sparx.form.handler.DialogNextActionProvider; <co
            id="util-class-eg-2" />
import com.netspective.sparx.form.DialogContext;

public class Util implements DialogNextActionProvider <co id="util-class-eg-3" />
{
  public String getDialogNextActionUrl(DialogContext dc, String defaultUrl) <co
            id="util-class-eg-4" />
  {
    return dc.getServletRootUrl(); <co id="util-class-eg-5" />
  }
}</programlisting>

        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="util-class-eg-1">
            <para>Defines the package for this class (<filename
            class="directory">app</filename> in this case)</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="util-class-eg-2">
            <para>Importing the required classes</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="util-class-eg-3">
            <para>The class <classname>Util</classname> Implements the Sparx
            <interfacename>DialogNextActionProvider</interfacename>
            interface.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="util-class-eg-4">
            <para>Implementing the method that gets the URL for the dialog's
            next action.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="util-class-eg-5">
            <para>Returns the root URL of the current dialog context. The URL
            in this case will be the one for the Books Application Home
            page.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>

        <para>To compile the Util.java, go to <guimenu>Project</guimenu> |
        <guisubmenu>Ant Build</guisubmenu> section in Console and execute the
        <sgmltag>Compile</sgmltag> target.</para>

        <para></para>

        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-build-compile.gif" />
        </screenshot>

        <para>The <filename>Util.java</filename> file is compiled and a
        compile message is displayed.</para>

        <para></para>

        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-build-compile-msg.gif" />
        </screenshot>

        <para>You can define the custom class, for handling the next action of
        your dialogs (forms), using the following XML declaration:</para>
      </example>

      <example>
        <title>Declaring Custom-Class for Dialog's Next Action
        Provider</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;navigation-tree&gt;
   &lt;dialog-next-action-provider class="app.Util"/&gt; <co
            id="declare-util-class-eg-1" />
&lt;/navigation-tree&gt;</programlisting>

        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="declare-util-class-eg-1">
            <para>Declaring custom class (<filename
            class="directory">app</filename>.<classname>Util</classname> in
            this case) for custom-handling of dialog's next action. The class
            name is fully qualified.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Testing the Books Application</title>

      <para>Congratulations! The Books Application is complete. Now you should
      open up your browser window and go to the Book Applicationâ€™s main page
      using the URL:
      http://<replaceable>host</replaceable>:<replaceable>port</replaceable>/<replaceable>appName</replaceable>.
      Assuming you are using localhost and port <literal>8080</literal> for
      your Resin server and <literal>nefs-sample-books</literal> as your
      application's name, the URL for Books Application Home Page becomes:
      <ulink
      url="http://localhost:8080/nefs-sample-books">http://localhost:8080/nefs-sample-books</ulink></para>

      <para></para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-books-app-home.gif" />
      </screenshot>

      <para>The Home page lists all the books available in your Books
      Application database along with the Edit and Delete buttons. Try adding
      a new book from the Add Book section.</para>

      <para></para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-books-app-add.gif" />
      </screenshot>

      <para>Enter the book information and click the <command>OK</command>
      button. You can see the newly added book in the list available on the
      Home page.</para>

      <para></para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-books-app-new-list.gif" />
      </screenshot>

      <para>Try editing the record of the book. Select the book from the list
      by clicking on its name. The Edit Book page is displayed containing the
      selected book's information.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-books-app-edit.gif" />
      </screenshot>

      <para>Try searching for books by genre or name, or any other field for
      that matter, by using the Search Books page.</para>

      <para></para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-books-app-search.gif" />
      </screenshot>

      <para>The result of the search is displayed in tabular form.</para>

      <para></para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-books-search-result.gif" />
      </screenshot>

      <para>You may see the SQL statement corresponding to a search criteria
      by clicking on the <emphasis>View Generated SQL</emphasis> check box on
      the Search Books page. The SQL statement is displayed along with the
      bind parameters and their values.</para>

      <note>
        <para>You may turn this option off in the production application by
        setting the <sgmltag>allow-debug</sgmltag> attribute of
        <sgmltag>select-dialog</sgmltag> tag within the corresponding query
        definition. See <xref linkend="desc-pres-dyn-qry" /></para>
      </note>

      <para></para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-books-app-search-qry.gif" />
      </screenshot>

      <para>Go to Home page and select the book to delete. The Delete Book
      page is displayed containing the selected book's information. Click on
      the Delete button to delete the selected book's record.</para>

      <para></para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-books-app-delete.gif" />
      </screenshot>

      <para>You may access the Books Application Console through the Console
      page. Use '<literal>console</literal>' and '<literal>console</literal>'
      (without quotes) for Console's <varname>User Id</varname> and
      <varname>Password</varname>.</para>

      <para></para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-books-app-console.gif" />
      </screenshot>

      <para>Try the Sample Apps Home page to see the NEFS Sample Apps Home
      Page loaded from the netspective web site.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-books-samples-page.gif" />
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Conclusion</title>

      <para>Your first Sparx application that does something meaningful is
      complete and you have gone through the shallowest parts of almost
      everything Sparx has to offer. You can now continue to improve the Books
      Application with newer ideas, delving deeper into Sparx or you can start
      a new application and use what you learned here to see how fast you can
      have a running system.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Console Application</title>

    <para>TODO: Link to Console's Tour. Documentation coming soon...</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Moving to Another Database</title>

    <para>TODO: Documentation coming soon...</para>
  </section>
</article>