<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Getting Started with the Netspective Enterprise Frameworks Suite
  (NEFS)</title>

  <para>The <emphasis>quickest</emphasis> way to evaluate the NEFS is to view
  all the documentation online and follow along with the online versions of
  the sample applications. Since all you need is a web browser, you can start
  learning about NEFS immediately. Because the applications are online, you
  will also be introduced to NEF&#39;s built-in remote development and team
  programming capabilities by seeing for yourself how you can review code and
  applications remotely. The sole disadvantage of the online evaluation is
  that you will not have the ability to dabble in or change the application
  code yourself.</para>

  <para>The <emphasis>recommended</emphasis> method of evaluating the NEF is
  to download sample applications and install them in your own application
  server. Each of the downloadable sample applications are provided as
  app-server-independent <filename>.war</filename> files. Each sample
  app&#39;s <filename>.war</filename> file contains everything you need,
  including all of the NEFS binaries, third-party libraries, and resources, to
  start using NEFS immediately. Once you have downloaded any
  <filename>.war</filename> file from our website, you have everything you
  need to start modifying and adding to the app. There is even a special
  sample application called the <emphasis>NEFS Starter</emphasis> that allows
  you to start writing your own applications using an empty template app.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Sampling the NEFS Online</title>

    <para>The <emphasis>Enterprise Sampler</emphasis> application, available
    at <ulink url="http://www.netspective.com">http://www.netspective.com</ulink>
    (by clicking the <emphasis>Try Online</emphasis> link), is the first NEFS
    sample application that you should try because it&#39;s designed to help
    sample important components of the presentation and user interfaces
    features of our Frameworks. The application contains complete instructions
    on what&#39;s available to sample and links to important features.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-home.gif" />
    </screenshot>

    <section>
      <title>Running the Sample Applications Online</title>

      <para>All of the NEFS sample application are available at <ulink
      url="http://www.netspective.com">http://www.netspective.com</ulink> (by
      clicking the <emphasis>Try It Online</emphasis> link from the Home
      page). Each of the sample applications have two links: one is a link to
      the application itself and the other is a link to it&#39;s
      <emphasis>Console</emphasis> Servlet.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Viewing XML Source Code in the Sampler</title>

      <para>The NEFS uses simple XML tags as its object construction and
      declaration language. The <emphasis>Enterprise Sampler</emphasis>
      application provides links on every page that allow you to learn how a
      few simple lines of XML can produce sophisticated web based
      applications.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Viewing Other Source Code and Application Files in a Browser</title>

      <para>The Netspective administration console, called the
      <emphasis>Enterprise Console</emphasis>, provides a complete file
      browser with color syntax highlighting for XML, JSP, Java, JavaScript,
      and SQL files – this file browser allows you to review source code for
      online sample applications or locally if you downloaded the sample
      applications.</para>

      <para>The Enterprise Console is a special Sparx Servlet that provides a
      browser-based administrative interface to all of the dynamic components
      and objects that NEFS produces. The Enterprise Console is automatically
      available to all NEF-based applications during development and each NEFS
      application has a private instance of the Console available at
      <literal>http://[server]/[appName]</literal><emphasis role="bold"><literal>/console</literal></emphasis>.
      When you log into the Console for Application X (.../appX/console)
      versus Y (.../appY/console) you will only see components for the
      appropriate application.</para>

      <important>
        <para>Each sample app features its own Console Servlet and the default
        login user name is &#39;<literal>console</literal>&#39; and the
        default login password is &#39;<literal>console</literal>&#39;.</para>
      </important>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-login.gif" />
      </screenshot>

      <para>Once you have logged into the Console for any particular
      application, all of the source files and folders are available for
      viewing. Simply click on the <guimenuitem>Project</guimenuitem> tab and
      then click <guimenuitem>Project Folders</guimenuitem> to view all of the
      folders contained in the application and <guimenuitem>Project Files</guimenuitem>
      to navigate all the directories and look at the project files. The first
      time you enter the Project Files section, you should see a list of all
      the directories that exist in the application’s root directory. You can
      click on any directory to navigate to it and view the list of files and
      sub-directories inside it.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-project-files.gif" />
      </screenshot>

      <para>If you click on any XML, JSP or Java source file, you should also
      be able to see the source for those files directly from the browser.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic
        fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-project-file-source.gif" />
      </screenshot>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using your own App Server to Sample the NEFS on your Workstation</title>

    <para>In order to sample the true power of the NEF, you should try the
    samples on your own workstation or server. This section describes the
    prerequisites you need to sample NEFS locally:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Java Developers Kit (JDK) 1.2, 1.3, or 1.4</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A Servlet Container (application server) supporting the Servlet
        2.2 or higher specification</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Make sure you have a Java Developer&#39;s Kit (JDK)</title>

      <para>Since NEFS is comprised of Java libraries, a fundamental
      requirement to develop applications with it is a Java SDK (the full SDK
      is required, the JRE will not be enough). You can obtain Sun’s official
      Java SDK from its Java web site at <ulink
      url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4/download.html">http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4/download.html</ulink>.
      This is a link to the Java 1.4 SDK but Java 1.2 and 1.3 will also work.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Make sure you have an Application Server (Servlet Container)</title>

      <para>Since Sparx works with standard J2EE application servers, a
      Servlet container is required if you&#39;re going to use Sparx. Both
      Axiom and Commons work in web-based or non-web-based applications but
      Sparx is a web application development library so an application server
      with a Servlet 2.2 or better container is necessary. Sparx-based
      applications have been tested on the following application servers:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat">Apache Tomcat</ulink>
          (free)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://www.caucho.com">Caucho Resin</ulink> (free
          for development, commercial license required for deployment)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://www.bea.com/framework.jsp?CNT=index.htm&#38;FP=/content/products/server">BEA
          WebLogic</ulink> (commercial)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://www.ibm.com/websphere">IBM WebSphere</ulink>
          (commercial)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://www.oracle.com/appserver/">ORACLE
          Application Server</ulink> (commercial)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://www.macromedia.com/software/jrun/">Macromedia
          JRun</ulink> (commercial)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>We recommend the <ulink url="http://www.caucho.com">Caucho Resin</ulink>
        application server if you&#39;re not familiar with other Servlet
        containers or if you&#39;re new to Java/J2EE application servers.
        It&#39;s an easy to install, easy to use, and fast Servlet container
        with advanced features that rival other more expensive application
        servers such as WebLogic and WebSphere. Resin is free for development
        use but requires a paid license before putting your application into
        production use. Rest assured though that all Sparx-based applications
        you write, even on Resin, will remain app-server neutral.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Use an Integrated Development Environment (IDE)</title>

      <para>You can also optionally install a Java integrated development
      environment (IDE) for developing NEFS applications. The Netspective
      Frameworks do not require any particular Java IDE and if you prefer to
      use simple text editors like vi, emacs, or <ulink
      url="http://www.textpad.com">TextPad</ulink> those will work just as
      well. We recommend the free <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org">Eclipse</ulink>
      IDE or very affordable and useful <ulink url="http://www.intellij.org">JetBrain’s
      IDEA</ulink> for those who are not already familiar with other IDEs.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Evaluating NEFS Using the Sample Applications</title>

      <para>To keep things simple, there&#39;s no special &#34;evaluation
      kit&#34; for NEFS -- instead you just download a sample application from
      <ulink url="http://www.netspective.com">http://www.netspective.com</ulink>
      (click &#34;Downloads&#34; at the top of the page then pick &#34;Sample
      Applications&#34; from the Downloads page). Once you download an
      application, just drop it into your favorite Servlet container
      (application server) and you&#39;ll be ready for the evaluation. Each of
      the sample applications are provided as app-server-independent <filename
      class="extension">.war</filename> files and each sample app&#39;s
      <filename class="extension">.war</filename> file includes all of the
      NEFS binary files, resources, etc. you need to use NEF. Once you have
      downloaded any <filename class="extension">.war</filename> file, you
      have everything you need to start modifying and adding to the app. The
      typical procedure is: <orderedlist><listitem><para>Download and install
      an application server (Servlet container).</para></listitem><listitem><para>Go
      to <ulink url="http://www.netspective.com">http://www.netspective.com</ulink>
      (click &#34;Downloads&#34; at the top of the page then pick &#34;Sample
      Applications&#34; from the Downloads page) and pick any application
      you&#39;re interested in evaluating.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Download
      the <filename class="extension">.war</filename> file and place it into
      the app server&#39;s web applications directory.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Start
      (or restart) the application server.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Use
      your browser to point to http://localhost:<replaceable>port</replaceable>/<replaceable>appName</replaceable>
      to run the application or http://localhost:<replaceable>port</replaceable>/<replaceable>appName</replaceable>/console
      to run the application&#39;s Console servlet.</para></listitem></orderedlist></para>

      <section>
        <title>Evaluating NEFS Sample Applications on Caucho Resin</title>

        <para>This section provides an overview of how to obtain, install, and
        start the <ulink url="http://www.caucho.com">Caucho Resin</ulink>
        application server and the <emphasis>NEFS Enterprise Sampler</emphasis>
        sample application. See the <ulink
        url="http://www.caucho.com/resin-3.0/install/install.xtp#quickstart">Resin
        QuickStart</ulink> document for the most up-to-date information.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Install JDK 1.3 or later if you&#39;re using Resin 2.1 or
            above. JDK 1.4 or later if you&#39;re using Resin 3.0 or above. On
            Unix, set the JAVA_HOME variable or link <filename
            class="directory">/usr/java</filename> to the Java home. On
            Windows, check to make sure the JDK installation set JAVA_HOME
            correctly.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink url="http://www.caucho.com/download/">Download</ulink>
            the latest Resin release (something like <filename>resin-x.y.z.zip</filename>,
            e.g. <filename>resin-3.0.4.zip</filename> or <filename>resin-3.0.4.tar.gz</filename>).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Uncompress (unzip/untar) the package into <filename
            class="directory">resin-x.y.z</filename>, e.g. <filename
            class="directory">C:\resin-3.0.4</filename>, or other directory.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click <ulink
            url="http://www.netspective.com/resources/downloads/nefs-sampler.war">here</ulink>
            to download the <emphasis>Sampler</emphasis> sample application
            and save it in <filename class="directory">resin-x.y.z\webapps</filename>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Start <filename>resin-x.y.z/bin/httpd.sh</filename> on Unix
            or <filename>resin-x.y.z/bin/httpd.exe</filename> on Win32. This
            will start up a local web server and the application server at the
            same time.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Browse <ulink url="http://localhost:8080">http://localhost:8080</ulink>
            to make sure Resin is working properly. If you do not see the
            Resin welcome page, please see the <ulink
            url="http://www.caucho.com/resin-3.0/install/index.xtp">Resin
            Installation</ulink> document for appropriate help. If Resin is
            not working properly, Sparx will not be able to run either.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Browse <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/nefs-sampler">http://localhost:8080/nefs-sampler</ulink>
            to run the application or <ulink
            url="http://localhost:8080/nefs-sampler/console">http://localhost:8080/nefs-sampler/console</ulink>
            to run the Hello Forms Console servlet.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>