<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Getting Started with the Netspective Enterprise Frameworks (NEF)</title>

  <para>The quickest way to evaluate the NEF is to view all the documentation
  online and follow along with the online versions of the applications created
  in the tutorials. The main advantages of this method are simplicity and
  speed. Since all you need is a web browser, you can start learning about NEF
  immediately. You will also be introduced to NEF&#39;s built-in remote
  development and team programming capabilities. The disadvantage is that you
  will not have the ability to dabble in or change the application code
  yourself.</para>

  <para>The recommended method of evaluating NEF is to download sample
  applications and install them in your own application server. The main
  advantage of using this method is that you will get a good hands-on look at
  NEF and, by the time you are through with the documentation and tutorials,
  you will be well on your way to developing your own applications using NEF.
  The only disadvantage is that you’ll need to download and install a Java
  Developer’s Kit (JDK), an application server, and one or more NEF sample
  applications on your own server.</para>

  <note>
    <para>Each of the downloadable sample applications are provided as
    app-server-independent <filename>.war</filename> files. Each sample
    app&#39;s <filename>.war</filename> file includes all of the NEF binary
    files, resources, and everything you need to use NEF. Once you have
    downloaded any <filename>.war</filename> file, you have everything you
    need to start modifying and adding to the app.</para>
  </note>

  <section>
    <title>Using the Netspective Enterprise Sampler to Sample the NEF Online</title>

    <para>The <emphasis>Enterprise Sampler</emphasis> application (available
    at <ulink url="http://sampler.netspective.com">http://sampler.netspective.com</ulink>
    or <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/nefs-sampler">http://localhost:8080/nefs-sampler</ulink>
    if you installed the sampler application in your own app server) is an NEF
    application that helps you navigate your way through all the NEF sample
    applications, test beds, and starter projects. The Sampler may also be
    used to obtain both the latest and archived releases of the Frameworks.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-home.gif" />
    </screenshot>

    <section>
      <title>Viewing Source Code in a Browser</title>

      <para>The Netspective administration console, called the
      <emphasis>Enterprise Console</emphasis>, provides a complete file
      browser with color syntax highlighting for XML, JSP, Java, JavaScript,
      and SQL files – this file browser allows you to review source code for
      sample applications at <ulink url="http://sampler.netspective.com">http://sampler.netspective.com</ulink>
      or locally if you downloaded the sample applications.</para>

      <para>The Enterprise Console is a Sparx Servlet that provides a
      browser-based administrative interface to all of the dynamic components
      and objects that NEF produces. The Enterprise Console is automatically
      available to all NEF-based applications during development and each NEF
      application has a private instance of the Console available at
      <literal>http://[server]/[appName]</literal><emphasis role="bold"><literal>/console</literal></emphasis>.
      When you log into the Console for Application X (.../appX/console)
      versus Y (.../appY/console) you will only see components for the
      appropriate application. The Console&#39;s default user name is &#39;<literal>console</literal>&#39;
      and the default password is &#39;<literal>console</literal>&#39;. Unless
      otherwise specified, that is the user name and password combination you
      should use if the Console prompts you to login.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-login.gif" />
      </screenshot>

      <para>Once you have logged into the Console for any particular
      application, all of the source files and folders are available for
      viewing. Simply click on the <guimenuitem>Project</guimenuitem> tab and
      then click <guimenuitem>Project Folders</guimenuitem> to view all of the
      folders contained in the application and <guimenuitem>Project Files</guimenuitem>
      to navigate all the directories and look at the project files. The first
      time you enter the Project Files section, you should see a list of all
      the directories that exist in the application’s root directory. You can
      click on any directory to navigate to it and view the list of files and
      sub-directories inside it.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-project-files.gif" />
      </screenshot>

      <para>If you click on any XML, JSP or Java source file, you should also
      be able to see the source for those files directly from the browser.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic
        fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-project-file-source.gif" />
      </screenshot>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using your own App Server to Sample the NEF on your Workstation</title>

    <para>In order to sample the true power of the NEF, you should try the
    samples on your own workstation or server. This section describes the
    prerequisites you need to sample NEF locally:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Java Developers Kit (JDK) 1.2, 1.3, or 1.4</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A Servlet Container (application server) supporting the Servlet
        2.2 or higher specification</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Make sure you have a Java Developer&#39;s Kit (JDK)</title>

      <para>Since NEF is comprised of Java libraries, a fundamental
      requirement to develop applications with it is a Java SDK (the full SDK
      is required, the JRE will not be enough). You can obtain Sun’s official
      Java SDK from its Java web site at <ulink
      url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4/download.html">http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4/download.html</ulink>.
      This is a link to the Java 1.4 SDK but Java 1.2 and 1.3 will also work.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Make sure you have an Application Server (Servlet Container)</title>

      <para>Since Sparx works with standard J2EE application servers, a
      Servlet container is required if you&#39;re going to use Sparx. Both
      Axiom and Commons work in web-based or non-web-based applications but
      Sparx is a web application development library so an application server
      with a Servlet 2.2 or better container is necessary. Sparx-based
      applications have been tested on the following application servers:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat">Apache Tomcat</ulink>
          (free)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://www.caucho.com">Caucho Resin</ulink> (free
          for development, commercial license required for deployment)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://www.bea.com/framework.jsp?CNT=index.htm&#38;FP=/content/products/server">BEA
          WebLogic</ulink> (commercial)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://www.ibm.com/websphere">IBM WebSphere</ulink>
          (commercial)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://www.oracle.com/appserver/">ORACLE
          Application Server</ulink> (commercial)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://www.macromedia.com/software/jrun/">Macromedia
          JRun</ulink> (commercial)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>We recommend the <ulink url="http://www.caucho.com">Caucho Resin</ulink>
        application server if you&#39;re not familiar with other Servlet
        containers or if you&#39;re new to Java/J2EE application servers.
        It&#39;s an easy to install, easy to use, and fast Servlet container
        with advanced features that rival other more expensive application
        servers such as WebLogic and WebSphere. Resin is free for development
        use but requires a paid license before putting your application into
        production use. Rest assured though that all Sparx-based applications
        you write, even on Resin, will remain app-server neutral.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Use an Integrated Development Environment (IDE)</title>

      <para>You can also optionally install a Java integrated development
      environment (IDE) for developing NEF applications. The Netspective
      Frameworks do not require any particular Java IDE and if you prefer to
      use simple text editors like vi, emacs, or <ulink
      url="http://www.textpad.com">TextPad</ulink> those will do just as well.
      We recommend the free <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org">Eclipse</ulink>
      IDE or very affordable and useful <ulink url="http://www.intellij.org">JetBrain’s
      IDEA</ulink> for those who are not already familiar with other IDEs.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Evaluating NEF Using the Sample Applications</title>

      <para>To keep things simple, there&#39;s no special &#34;evaluation
      kit&#34; for NEF -- instead you just download a sample application from
      <ulink url="http://sampler.netspective.com">http://sampler.netspective.com</ulink>,
      drop it into your favorite Servlet container (application server) and
      you&#39;ll be ready for the evaluation. Each of the sample applications
      are provided as app-server-independent <filename class="extension">.war</filename>
      files and each sample app&#39;s <filename class="extension">.war</filename>
      file includes all of the NEF binary files, resources, etc. you need to
      use NEF. Once you have downloaded any <filename class="extension">.war</filename>
      file, you have everything you need to start modifying and adding to the
      app. The typical procedure is: <orderedlist><listitem><para>Download and
      install an application server (Servlet container).</para></listitem><listitem><para>Go
      to <ulink url="http://sampler.netspective.com">http://sampler.netspective.com</ulink>
      and pick any application you&#39;re interested in evaluating.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Download
      the <filename class="extension">.war</filename> file and place it into
      the app server&#39;s web applications root.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Start
      (or restart) the application server.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Use
      your browser to point to http://localhost:<replaceable>port</replaceable>/<replaceable>appName</replaceable>
      to run the application or http://localhost:<replaceable>port</replaceable>/<replaceable>appName</replaceable>/console
      to run the application&#39;s Console servlet.</para></listitem></orderedlist></para>

      <section>
        <title>Evaluating NEF Sample Applications on Caucho Resin</title>

        <para>This section provides an overview of how to obtain, install, and
        start the <ulink url="http://www.caucho.com">Caucho Resin</ulink>
        application server and the Hello Forms sample application. See the
        <ulink
        url="http://www.caucho.com/resin-3.0/install/install.xtp#quickstart">Resin
        QuickStart</ulink> document for the most up-to-date information.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Install JDK 1.3 or late if you&#39;re using Resin 2.1 or
            above. JDK 1.4 or later if you&#39;re using Resin 3.0 or above. On
            Unix, set the JAVA_HOME variable or link <filename
            class="directory">/usr/java</filename> to the Java home. On
            Windows, check to make sure the JDK installation set JAVA_HOME
            correctly.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink url="http://www.caucho.com/download/">Download</ulink>
            the latest Resin release (something like <filename>resin-x.y.z.zip</filename>,
            e.g. <filename>resin-3.0.4.zip</filename> or <filename>resin-3.0.4.tar.gz</filename>).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Uncompress (unzip/untar) the package into <filename
            class="directory">C:\resin-x.y.z</filename>, e.g. <filename
            class="directory">C:\resin-3.0.4</filename>, or other directory.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click <ulink
            url="http://sampler.netspective.com/nefs-sampler/downloads/nefs-sample-hello-forms.war">here</ulink>
            to download the Hello Forms sample application and save it in
            <filename class="directory">c:\resin-x.y.z\webapps</filename>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Start <filename>resin-x.y.z/bin/httpd.sh</filename> on Unix
            or <filename>resin-x.y.z/bin/httpd.exe</filename> on Win32. This
            will start up a local web server and the application server at the
            same time.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Browse <ulink url="http://localhost:8080">http://localhost:8080</ulink>
            to make sure Resin is working properly. If you do not see the
            Resin welcome page, please see the <ulink
            url="http://www.caucho.com/resin-3.0/install/index.xtp">Resin
            Installation</ulink> document for appropriate help. If Resin is
            not working properly, Sparx will not be able to run either.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Browse <ulink
            url="http://localhost:8080/nefs-sample-hello-forms">http://localhost:8080/nefs-sample-hello-forms</ulink>
            to run the application or <ulink
            url="http://localhost:8080/nefs-sample-hello-forms/console">http://localhost:8080/nefs-sample-hello-forms/console</ulink>
            to run the Hello Forms Console servlet.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>