<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY __nef-assumptions__drd5vrj0 SYSTEM "../nef-reusable-content/nef-assumptions.xml">
<!ENTITY __nef-sampler-setup__drd8289e SYSTEM "../nef-reusable-content/nef-sampler-setup.xml">
]>
<article>
  <title>NEFS Sampler Tutorial</title>

  <section>
    <title>Objectives</title>

    <para>Welcome to the NEFS Sampler Tutorial (Tour)! This tutorial aims at
    giving you a tour of the NEFS Sampler. It facilitates your learning by
    reducing the learning time through quick familiarization with various
    Sampler sections. You don't have to worry about learning the use of
    Sampler. Instead, you can concentrate on the core concepts being
    highlighted by the Sampler sections.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Learning Objectives Checklist</title>

      <para>At the end of this tutorial, you should be able to
      understand:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the objectives of NEFS Sampler</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>how to set up the NEFS Sampler at your application
          server</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>how to view the XDM code within NEFS Sampler</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>purpose of NEFS Sampler sections</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>usage of NEFS Sampler sections</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  &__nef-assumptions__drd5vrj0;

  <section>
    <title>Starting the NEFS Sampler</title>

    <para>There are two ways of exploring the NEFS Sampler:</para>

    <section>
      <title>Trying the NEFS Sampler Application Online</title>

      <para>You may test the Sampler Application online at <ulink
      url="http://www.netspective.com/corp/products/frameworks/try">http://www.netspective.com/corp/products/frameworks/try</ulink>
      All you need is a web browser and you can start using the NEF Sampler
      immediately.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-test-online.gif" />
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    &__nef-sampler-setup__drd8289e;
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>NEFS Sampler Objectives</title>

    <para>As the name suggests, the purpose of NEFS Sampler Application is to
    give you an idea of how easy it is to build J2EE web applications using
    the powerful building blocks provided by our Java Frameworks. The NEFS
    Sampler uses an interactive mode thus making it easy to understand and use
    the samples. It includes various examples of creating forms and input
    fields, performing a variety of different data validations and executing
    forms to provide end-user functionality.</para>

    <para>Although you start with simple NEFS usage examples, as you learn
    more about Sparx and Axiom you will see that flexibility and extensibility
    are also a part of their attributes.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Viewing the XDM Code</title>

    <para>The eXtensible Markup Language (XML) plays an important role in
    NEF's ease of use, extensibility, and code generation. NEF declarations
    are performed using XML -- all dialogs, fields, validation rules, some
    conditional processing, all SQL statements, dynamic queries, configuration
    files, database schemas, and many other resources are stored in XML files
    that are re-usable across applications.</para>

    <para><acronym>XDM</acronym> is an acronym for "XML Data Model" and is
    designed to help Java programmers construct and configure Java objects
    using XML files without worrying about parsing and error checking. The
    <filename class="directory">APP_ROOT</filename>/<filename
    class="directory">WEB-INF</filename>/<filename
    class="directory">sparx</filename>/<filename>project.xml</filename> file
    uses XDM to declare all project components.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>In the Sampler app if you see the <guiicon>XML</guiicon> icon along
    with a <emphasis>View Page XDM Code</emphasis> link, at the bottom of the
    page, you can view the Netspective Xml Data Model (XDM) source code for
    various objects on the page. This helps you view the XML code and see it
    working on the same page.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-XDM-link.gif" />
    </screenshot>

    <para>The <guiicon>XML</guiicon> icon also appears under various panels
    (like forms/dialogs) to see their code as well.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-view-panel-XDM.gif" />
    </screenshot>

    <para>Clicking on the <emphasis>View Page XDM Code</emphasis> link to see
    the XML code (as shown below): [TODO: Put image with the callouts]</para>

    <screenshot>
      <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-show-XDM.gif" />
    </screenshot>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The link to Hide the currently visible XDM code. Clicking on
        this link hides the currently visible XDM code.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Location of the currently open XDM code in the application's
        project file (<filename class="directory">WEB-INF</filename>/<filename
        class="directory">sparx</filename>/<filename>project.xml</filename>).
        Clicking on this link takes you to the <guimenu>Project</guimenu> |
        <guisubmenu>Project Files</guisubmenu> section of the Sampler app's
        Console, with Sampler app project file being displayed in browse
        mode.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-view-prj-file.gif" />
        </screenshot>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Java class file being instantiated for this page. Clicking on
        this link takes you to the <guimenu>Project</guimenu> |
        <guisubmenu>Project Files</guisubmenu> section of the Sampler app's
        Console, with the selected java file
        (<classname>AppPage.java</classname> in this case) being displayed in
        browse mode.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-view-java.gif" />
        </screenshot>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>XDM code (from the Sampler app project file) corresponding to
        the currently opened page.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Viewing Project Folder and Files</title>

    <para>At the end of the Sampler App Home page, there is a link for browing
    through all the source directories and files of the Sampler App.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-prj-folder-link.gif" />
    </screenshot>

    <para>When you click on the <emphasis>browse</emphasis> link, it takes you
    to the <guimenu>Project</guimenu> | <guisubmenu>Project Files</guisubmenu>
    section of Sampler app Console, displaying all the source folders and
    files for the Sampler app.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-prj-folder.gif" />
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>NEFS Sampler Main Components</title>

    <para>The NEFS Sampler groups the samples into following logical
    sections:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Home</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Forms Input</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Forms Execution</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Access Control</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Play</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Sitemap</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Console</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Sample Apps Home</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Home</title>

      <para>This is the Welcome page for the Sampler. It outlines the
      objectives of the Sampler and also contains a list of links pointing to
      the logical sections of the Sampler. You may access the Sampler sections
      by these links or the tabs provided the top of the page.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-app-home.gif" />
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Forms Input</title>

      <para>This page and its chldren pages contain samples that demonstrate
      how forms and input fields are created in Sparx. There are many examples
      that show how quick and easy it is to set up forms to accept input
      values and automatically validate them. The examples contained in this
      section are further divided into sub-categories. The Forms Input page
      contains a list of links to its children pages containing the
      categorized example pages. Links to these children pages are also
      provided through a submenu bar under the Forms Input tab.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-form-inputs-main.gif" />
      </screenshot>

      <section>
        <title>Text</title>

        <para>The Framework provides different styles of displaying text input
        fields. One is a simple one line text input field while another is a
        multi-line text input field.</para>

        <para>The Line-based text input examples are included under
        <guimenuitem>Line-oriented</guimenuitem> submenu.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Sample Page for Line-oriented Text Fields</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-line.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The sample text fields on this page show the usage of static
        text fields, input text fields (text boxes), <type>email</type> fields
        and masked fields for password entry. You can also see how to
        associate hints with a particular text input field. The example also
        implements field validation. Click on the <command>OK</command> button
        to see how field validation messages are displayed.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Field Validation Messages</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-text-block.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>At times you need multi-line fields (e.g. text area) for your
        text input. The <guimenuitem>Block-oriented</guimenuitem> submenu
        contains examples highlighting the block based text input. <figure>
            <title>Sample Page for Block-oriented Text Fields</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-text-block.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>This page shows the usage of <type>memo</type> and template
        fields using custom <acronym>CSS</acronym> and
        <acronym>HTML</acronym>. This sample page also incorporates error
        messages using message boxes (as shown in the above image).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Numbers</title>

        <para>This page demonstrates the usage of various types of numeric
        fields that are available: float, integer, currency, phone, and zip
        code. Each type have their own validation rules and formatting
        patterns.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Sample Page for Numeric Fields</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-numbers.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Boolean</title>

        <para>This page demonstrates usage of boolean fields which are fields
        that can only have a value that is either true or false. There are
        several display styles available for boolean fields: radio,
        check-alone, popup, and combo.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Sample Page for Boolean Fields</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-boolean.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Selection</title>

        <para>This page demonstrates how to create and use fields that allow
        selection of values. There are several styles available: list,
        multidual, multilist, combo, radio, and multicheck. You can also see
        the implementation for <type>popup</type> based select field.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Sample Page for Select Fields</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-select.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Conditional Select</title>

        <para>This page demonstrates how to create and use fields that allow
        selection of values and auto submit forms that will do other data
        population from the server side (for conditional values).</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Sample Page for Conditional Select Fields</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-conditional-select.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Grids</title>

        <para>This page demonstrates how to create and use grid and composite
        fields. A composite field can be described as a logical field that
        contains several children fields. Usually, a grid field will have
        multiple composite fields which act as rows.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Sample Page for Grid and CompositeFields</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-grids.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Conditionals</title>

        <para>This page demonstrates how flags and values can be applied to a
        dialog field based on conditionals defined for that field. Conditional
        fields are fields whose state depends upon the state of other entities
        (in this case, other fields called <emphasis>partner</emphasis>
        fields).</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Sample Page for Conditional Fields</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-conditional.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Popups</title>

        <para>This page demonstrates how to create and use popup fields. Sparx
        provides a feature to display a popup dialog box when a popup icon is
        clicked and values from a selection in the popup can be returned to
        the main window. Popup fields are visually identifiable by their
        special magnifying glass icon beside them.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Sample Page for Popup Fields</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-popups.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Date/Time</title>

        <para>This page demonstrates how to create and use date/time fields.
        There are several versions of date/time fields that are available:
        time, date, date and time, and duration.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Sample Page for Date/TimeFields</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-sampler-date-time.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Advanced</title>

        <para>This page and its children pages are for demonstrating more
        advanced usage of the built-in features of the dialog fields.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Forms Execution</title>

      <para></para>

      <section>
        <title>Director</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Templates</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Handlers</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Inheritance</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Delegation</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Access Control</title>

      <para></para>

      <section>
        <title>Change Role</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Test 1</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Test 2</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Test 3</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Play</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sitemap</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Console</title>

      <para>Like every other NEFS application, the Sampler also has a Console.
      This Console can be accessed through the Console section. You will see
      the application Console login screen.</para>

      <para><screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-login.gif" />
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>The Console's default User Id is <literal>'console</literal>' and
      the default Password is <literal>'console'</literal>(each without
      quotes). Unless otherwise specified, that is the User Id and Password
      combination you should use if the Console prompts you to login. Please
      refer to the <emphasis>Enterprise Console Tour</emphasis> for more
      details about the Console.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sample Apps Home</title>

      <para>This section takes you to the Sample Apps Home page on the
      netspective web site.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-books-samples-page.gif" />
      </screenshot>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</article>