<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section>
  <title>Sparx Navigation Tree Overview</title>

  <para>The NEFS presentation layer tags are broken up into several groups:
  navigation, forms/fields, on-screen validation, and conditional processing.
  Almost all of the presentation layer tags are managed by Sparx.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction to Navigation Declaration Tags</title>

    <para>The navigation tags comprise primarily the
    <sgmltag>navigation-tree</sgmltag>, <sgmltag>page</sgmltag>, and
    <sgmltag>body</sgmltag> tags. These are very high-level tags that provide
    a great deal of functionality without requiring any HTML or JSP. However,
    if you need to customize the behavior you have full access to the APIs
    through both inheritance and delegation. You focus on the hierarchy,
    specify the structure and rules and NEF will do the rest. The Sparx
    navigation system fully implements MVC (model-view-controller) design
    pattern.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Navigation Tags in the Presentation Layer</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;project xmlns:xdm="http://www.netspective.org/Framework/Commons/XMLDataModel"&gt;
...

&lt;<emphasis>navigation-tree</emphasis> name="app" default="yes"&gt; <co
            id="declare-nav-eg-1" />

    &lt;<emphasis>page</emphasis> name="home" default="yes" caption="Hello" heading="Hello World!"&gt; <co
            id="declare-nav-eg-2" />
        &lt;<emphasis>body</emphasis>&gt; <co id="declare-nav-eg-3" />
            &lt;![CDATA[
            This is the 'Hello World' app. Click &lt;a href="next-steps"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see what's next.
            ]]&gt;
        &lt;/body&gt;
    &lt;/page&gt;

    &lt;page name="next-steps" caption="Next Steps" heading="What's next?"&gt;
        &lt;body <emphasis>source</emphasis>="next-steps.ftl"/&gt; <co
            id="declare-nav-eg-4" />
    &lt;/page&gt;

    &lt;page name="some-stuff" caption="Panels instead of Body"&gt;
        &lt;<emphasis>panels</emphasis>&gt; <co id="declare-nav-eg-5" />
             &lt;panel type="command" command="query,org.get-sponsor-info-by-id,-,-,-,detail-compressed"/&gt;
             &lt;panel type="command" command="query,org.get-org-addresses-by-id,-,-,-,report-compressed" /&gt;
        &lt;/panels&gt;
    &lt;/page&gt;

    &lt;page name="sampler" caption="Sampler" <emphasis>redirect</emphasis>="vs-expr:${netspective-url:sampler}"/&gt; <co
            id="declare-nav-eg-6" />
    &lt;page name="sampler" caption="Sampler" <emphasis>include</emphasis>="/some/file.jsp"/&gt; <co
            id="declare-nav-eg-7" />
    &lt;page name="sampler" caption="Sampler" <emphasis>forward</emphasis>="/some/file.jsp"/&gt; <co
            id="declare-nav-eg-8" />

    &lt;page name="add" caption="Add Book" <emphasis>command</emphasis>="dialog,schema.db.Book_Info,add"/&gt; <co
            id="declare-nav-eg-9" />
    &lt;page name="edit" caption="Edit Book" command="dialog,schema.db.Book_Info,edit"
          require-request-param="id" retain-params="id"&gt;
        &lt;<emphasis>missing-params-body</emphasis>&gt; <co
            id="declare-nav-eg-10" />
           Please choose a book to edit from the &amp;lt;a href='home'&amp;gt; books list&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.
        &lt;/missing-params-body&gt;
    &lt;/page&gt;
&lt;/navigation-tree&gt;</programlisting>

        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="declare-nav-eg-1">
            <para>The <sgmltag>navigation-tree</sgmltag> tag starts out the
            definition of a tree. You may declare as many navigation trees as
            your application needs. Consider different trees for different
            users (based on personalization) or a different tree for each
            access-control role (for security) or any other criteria required
            by your application. Each tree has a name and may be marked with
            <sgmltag>default</sgmltag>=<literal>yes</literal> if it is to be
            the default tree. Which tree is actually used by the application
            may be specfied as a servlet parameter or chosen dynamically at
            runtime based on some processing rules.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-nav-eg-2">
            <para>Each <sgmltag>navigation-tree</sgmltag> tag one or more
            <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tags that define what pages should be
            visible to the user. Each <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag supports
            common things like the page's name (unique identifier), a caption
            (what might show up in a tab or menu), a heading, and
            title.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-nav-eg-3">
            <para>Each <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag may have an optional
            <sgmltag>body</sgmltag> tag with contents directly specified as
            XML content. You can use the CDATA XML element to escape HTML
            tags. The content of the <sgmltag>body</sgmltag> tag is treated as
            a <ulink url="http://www.freemarker.org">FreeMarker</ulink>
            template by default.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-nav-eg-4">
            <para>The <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag's <sgmltag>body</sgmltag>
            tag may instead specify a source attribute that indicates the
            given file is a a <ulink
            url="http://www.freemarker.org">FreeMarker</ulink> template
            relative to the <filename class="directory">APP_ROOT</filename>
            directory. Other template engines like JSP are also
            supported.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-nav-eg-5">
            <para>The <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag's <sgmltag>body</sgmltag>
            tag may be replaced with the <sgmltag>panels</sgmltag> tag to have
            automatic layouts of mutliple panels.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-nav-eg-6">
            <para>The <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag may specify a redirect
            attribute to automatically redirect to another page whenever it is
            chosen.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-nav-eg-7">
            <para>The <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag may specify an include
            attribute to simply insert the contents of another web resource
            directly into the body.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-nav-eg-8">
            <para>The <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag may specify a forward
            attribute to forward the request to another web resource (this is
            the same as Servlet forwarding not HTTP forwarding).</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-nav-eg-9">
            <para>The <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag may specify a command
            attribute to use the Command pattern and delegate the body to a
            <interfacename>com.netspective.commons.command.Command</interfacename>
            interface. These are very high-level commands like interacting
            with a dialog and displaying the results of a query that can be
            defined elsewhere and called on different pages.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="declare-nav-eg-10">
            <para>The <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag may specify required request
            parameters and optionally produce automatic error messages when
            they are not provided.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
      </example><note>
        <para>Almost all <sgmltag>page</sgmltag> tag attributes support
        <emphasis>Value Sources</emphasis> for their values so the values may
        be static or dynamic. This allows, for example the captions, headings,
        and all user-visible values to be properly placed in property files or
        other external resources and mapped in a language-specific manner for
        internationlization purposes. The important thing to understand is
        that even though the declarations are in a static XML file, the values
        of the descriptors are capable of being dynamic.</para>
      </note><note>
        <para>Please see the <ulink
        url="http://www.netspective.com/corp/resources/support/docs/nef-manual/index.html">NEF
        User's Manual</ulink> for instructions on how to use the Console to
        review tag documentation and use the Tags Tree to get further details
        on the <sgmltag>navigation-tree</sgmltag> and <sgmltag>page</sgmltag>
        tags.</para>
      </note></para>
  </section>
</section>