<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section>
  <title>Setting up the Starter Application</title>

  <para>For creation of a new NEF based application, you will need to download
  the Starter Application. The starter application is just an empty
  application that contains the minimal set of files required for NEF web
  applications. It doesn't do anything particularly useful but you can use
  this sample as your template for the new project.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Downloading the Starter Application</title>

    <para>You can download the NEF Starter Application file from <ulink
    url="http://www.netspective.com/corp/downloads/frameworks/samples">http://www.netspective.com/corp/downloads/frameworks/samples</ulink></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setting up the Starter Application (Using Application
    Server)</title>

    <section>
      <title>Auto Deploying the Starter Application (Using Application
      Server)</title>

      <para>Copy the downloaded <filename>nefs-starter-empty.war</filename>
      file to the <filename class="directory">webapps</filename> folder of
      your servlet container (application server) and run (or restart) the
      application server. This creates an Application Directory Structure (see
      <xref linkend="nef-app-dir-structure" />), containing the necessary NEF
      files and sub-folders, under the <filename
      class="directory">webapps</filename> folder of the application
      server.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setting up the Starter Application Manually</title>

      <para>Some servlet containers (application servers) may not auto deploy
      the war files. In such cases you need to manually set up your starter
      application using the following steps:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create a new folder in the <filename
          class="directory">webapps</filename> folder of your application
          server. Change this folder's name to <filename
          class="directory">nefs-starter-empty</filename> </para>

          <figure>
            <title>Creating a New Folder for NEFS Starter Application</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-starter-new-folder.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Extract the contents of
          <filename>nefs-starter-empty.war</filename> file into this newly
          created folder. You may use any ZIP file extraction utility, such as
          <ulink url="http://www.winzip.com/downwz.htm">WinZip</ulink> or
          <ulink url="http://www.rarsoft.com/download.htm">WinRAR</ulink>, for
          this purpose.</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Extracting nefs-starter-app.war File</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="./resources/images/screen-extract-starter-app.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>This creates an Application Directory Structure (see <xref
          linkend="nef-app-dir-structure" />), containing the necessary NEF
          files and sub-folders, within the <filename
          class="directory">nefs-starter-empty</filename> folder.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Testing the Starter Application in a Browser</title>

    <para>Use a web browser to access the root of the starter application
    using the URL of the form
    http://<replaceable>host</replaceable>:<replaceable>port</replaceable>/nefs-starter-empty.
    If everything worked as it should, you will see the Starter Application
    Welcome Page.</para>

    <para><screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-starter-home.gif" />
      </screenshot></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Verifying the Console</title>

    <para>Use a browser to access the Console of the Starter Application. This
    will ensure not just the proper configuration of the application but also
    its proper configuration in relax to Sparx. In a web browser, we can go to
    the following URL:
    http://<replaceable>host</replaceable>:<replaceable>port</replaceable>/nefs-starter-empty/console.
    If everything is working, you will see the application Console login
    screen.</para>

    <para><screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="./resources/images/screen-console-login.gif" />
      </screenshot></para>

    <para>Congratulations! You now have an empty application upon which you
    can build. You can log in to your application's Console. The Console's
    default User Id is <literal>'console</literal>' and the default Password
    is <literal>'console'</literal>(each without quotes). Unless otherwise
    specified, that is the User Id and Password combination you should use if
    the Console prompts you to login.</para>
  </section>
</section>