<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section>
  <title>Assumptions</title>

  <para>For the purpose of this tutorial, we will be assuming that you
  installed the following:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Java Developer's Kit (JDK) 1.2, 1.3 or 1.4 See <xref
      linkend="desc-download-jdk" /></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>An Application Server (servlet container) supporting the Servlet
      2.2 or higher specification See <xref
      linkend="desc-app-server" /></para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>We assume that you are using the default port <literal>8080</literal>
  for your web server. If you chose different values for the installation path
  and the port number, you should substitute the paths and the URLs in our
  example with your values as needed. This tutorial also assumes your
  familiarity with XML, SQL, Java, Servlets and JDBC.</para>

  <section id="desc-download-jdk">
    <title>Downloading Java Developer's Kit (JDK)</title>

    <para>Since NEFS comprises Java libraries, a fundamental requirement to
    develop applications with it is a Java SDK (the full SDK is required, the
    JRE will not be enough). You can obtain Sun’s official Java SDK from its
    Java web site at <ulink
    url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4/download.html">http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4/download.html</ulink>.
    This is a link to the Java 1.4 SDK but Java 1.2 and 1.3 will also
    work.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="desc-app-server">
    <title id="desc-servlet-container">Application Server (Servlet
    Container)</title>

    <para>Since Sparx works with standard J2EE application servers, a Servlet
    container is required if you're going to use Sparx. Both Axiom and Commons
    work in web-based or non-web-based applications but Sparx is a web
    application development library so an application server with a Servlet
    2.2 or better container is necessary. Sparx-based applications have been
    tested on the following application servers:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat">Apache
        Tomcat</ulink> (free)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.caucho.com">Caucho Resin</ulink> (free
        for development, commercial license required for deployment)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.bea.com/framework.jsp?CNT=index.htm&amp;FP=/content/products/server">BEA
        WebLogic</ulink> (commercial)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.ibm.com/websphere">IBM WebSphere</ulink>
        (commercial)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.oracle.com/appserver/">ORACLE Application
        Server</ulink> (commercial)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.macromedia.com/software/jrun/">Macromedia
        JRun</ulink> (commercial)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <note>
      <para>We recommend the <ulink url="http://www.caucho.com">Caucho
      Resin</ulink> application server if you're not familiar with other
      Servlet containers or if you're new to Java/J2EE application servers.
      It's an easy to install, easy to use, and fast Servlet container with
      advanced features that rival other more expensive application servers
      such as WebLogic and WebSphere. Resin is free for development use but
      requires a paid license before putting your application into production
      use. Rest assured though that all Sparx-based applications you write,
      even on Resin, will remain app-server neutral.</para>
    </note>
  </section>
</section>