<?xml version="1.0"?>

<netspective>
    <release>
        <product name="Sparx" version="7.0.6"/>
        <change-log>
            <summary>Minor enhancements</summary>
            <change-log-entry>
                <![CDATA[
                Added new Radeox wiki parser and template processor. Now you can define a page like the following:<p>
                <code>
                &lt;page ...><br>
                    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&lt;body type="wiki" source-file="name-of-file-value-source"/><br>
                    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&lt;body type="wiki" source-value="value-source-with-content"/><br>
                    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&lt;body type="wiki"><br>
                       &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;snipSnap wiki content filters and macros<br>
                    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&lt;/body><p>
                </code>
                This allows treating the content of a page (or panel) as Wiki text instead of freemarker or other templating system.
                ]]>
            </change-log-entry>
        </change-log>
    </release>

    <release>
        <product name="Commons" version="7.0.4"/>

        <change-log>
            <summary>Minor enhancement</summary>
            <change-log-entry>
                Allowed template processor to become a template consumer. This allows templates like &lt;template-processor-type
                name="abc" class="x.y.z"/&gt; to be defined in xml and then later used like &lt;body type="abc"/&gt;.
            </change-log-entry>
        </change-log>
    </release>

    <release>
        <product name="Commons" version="7.0.3"/>
        <change-log>
            <summary>Minor Bug Fixed</summary>
            <change-log-entry>Added nullity check that was preventing the Project DTD from being generated after store procedures were added.</change-log-entry>
        </change-log>
    </release>


    <release>
        <product name="Axiom" version="7.0.6"/>
        <change-log>
            <summary>Minor bug fixes and enhancements</summary>
            <change-log-entry>
                Fixed problem where the 'query' value source was complaining and not setting certain result styles.
            </change-log-entry>
            <change-log-entry>
                Added ability to return an accessor based on Index instead of only a column since indexes could
                have more than one column.
            </change-log-entry>
        </change-log>
    </release>


    <release>
        <product name="Sparx" version="7.0.5"/>
        <change-log>
            <summary>Minor enhancements</summary>
            <change-log-entry>
                Added special validation in the SchemaRecordEditorDialog to make sure that when updating and inserting a record
                unique constrains are not violated.  This additional validation takes into account unique columns and indexes
                so that if a combination of a set of columns need to be unique, that constraint is checked against the database
                before updating or inserting that row.
            </change-log-entry>
        </change-log>
    </release>


    <release>
        <product name="Axiom" version="7.0.5"/>
        <change-log>
            <summary>Minor enhancements</summary>
            <change-log-entry>
                Added special check in Update DML SQL for auto-inc columns. Now, if an auto-inc column is being updated
                the database policy will be queried to see if it should be removed from the Update DML SQL statement.
            </change-log-entry>
        </change-log>
    </release>


    <release>
        <product name="Sparx" version="7.0.4"/>
        <change-log>
            <summary>Minor enhancements</summary>
            <change-log-entry>
                Added new StandardTemplateNavigationSkin that allows freemarker-template based navigation skins.
                This allow non-java-based navigation skins to be created for content-heavy sites (as opposed to app-heavy sites).
            </change-log-entry>
        </change-log>
    </release>


    <release>
        <product name="Commons" version="7.0.2"/>
        <change-log>
            <summary>Minor refactoring</summary>
            <change-log-entry>Moved the redirect value source to be auto registered (was previously in sparx.xml but it shouldn't have been there).</change-log-entry>
        </change-log>
    </release>


    <release>
        <product name="Axiom" version="7.0.4"/>
        <change-log>
            <summary>Minor enhancements</summary>
            <change-log-entry>When generating the SQL to retrieve, insert, update or delete records, there is an option now to prefix the
                table names with the schema name.  This useful when the tables are owned by a different user than
                the one specified in the data source for connectivity.</change-log-entry>
        </change-log>
    </release>


    <release>
        <product name="Sparx" version="7.0.3"/>
        <change-log>
            <summary>Minor bug fixes and enhancements</summary>
            <change-log-entry>
                Fixed problem where tabbed panels did not remember their state across page views. Now cookies are
                being set properly so that minimized panels and tabbed panels do proper state management.
            </change-log-entry>
            <change-log-entry>
                Fixed problem where Console was logging out erroneously after a few page views on IE. It seems that
                IE has a limit to the number of cookies allowed and after too many cookies it starts removing older
                cookies (which kills JSESSIONID). Now,
                Sparx 7.0.3 has consolidated numerous cookies into a smaller
                number to help prevent against accidental removal of JSESSIONID. This problem was specific to
                IE and did not seem to affect Mozilla or Safari.
            </change-log-entry>
        </change-log>
    </release>


    <release>
        <product name="Axiom" version="7.0.3"/>
        <change-log>
            <summary>Minor bug fixes</summary>
            <change-log-entry>When locating the JDBC driver class in &lt;connection-provider&gt;, error message now shows the actual
                driver class and not the value source spec in case the class is not found.</change-log-entry>
            <change-log-entry>
                In SQL DDL generator, added check to see if column is required by app or dbms in order to generate the NOT NULL constraint.
                Before this change, only the isRequiredByDmbs() flag was checked.
            </change-log-entry>
        </change-log>
    </release>


    <release>
        <product name="Sparx" version="7.0.2"/>
        <change-log>
            <summary>Minor bug fixes</summary>
            <change-log-entry><![CDATA[In
                <code>com.netspective.sparx.theme.basic BasicHtmlTabularReportPanelSkin</code>, updated the
                code to check if the
                <code>title</code> attribute of the
                <code>panel/report/actions/action</code> tag is
                not null before rendering it. This
                <code>title</code> attribute is typically only used in selectable
                reports.]]>
            </change-log-entry>
        </change-log>
    </release>


    <release>
        <product name="Axiom" version="7.0.2"/>
        <change-log>
            <summary>Minor code cleanup</summary>
            <change-log-entry>Removed some System.out debugging statements left in the stored procedure classes.</change-log-entry>
        </change-log>
    </release>


    <release>
        <product name="Commons" version="7.0.1"/>
        <product name="Axiom" version="7.0.1"/>
        <product name="Sparx" version="7.0.1"/>
        <change-log>
            <summary>New features</summary>
            <change-log-entry>
                <![CDATA[
                Improved support for error pages with additional features in &lt;navigation-tree&gt;'s and
                &lt;page&gt;'s &lt;error-page&gt; tag.
                ]]>
            </change-log-entry>
            <change-log-entry>
                <![CDATA[
                Changed the delimiter of the
                <code>ListValueSourceCommand</code> from comma
                <code>[,]</code> to
                pipe
                <code>[|]</code> so that embedded value sources in the command will work properly. Before this
                change, only value sources that didn't contain commas in their specs were allowed.
                ]]>
            </change-log-entry>
            <change-log-entry>
                <![CDATA[
                Changed the rule for DialogContext Beans generation so that only
                <code>&lt;dialog&gt;</code> tags that have the
                <code>&lt;dialog ... generate-dcb="yes"/&gt;</code> attribute will generate dialog context beans.
                ]]>
            </change-log-entry>
            <change-log-entry>
                <![CDATA[
                Added new attribute called
                <code>allow-execute-with-cancel-button</code> to the
                <code>&lt;dialog&gt;</code> tag which allows
                execution of the dialog even when the Cancel button is pressed. Currently it is up to the developer
                to check for it and do the appropriate action in the execution listeners.
                ]]>
            </change-log-entry>
        </change-log>
    </release>

</netspective>